<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A remonstrance presented to O.P. Feb. 4. 1655. By J.G. D.D. A son, servant, and supplicant for the Church of England: in behalf of many thousands his distressed brethren (ministers of the Gospel, and other good schollars) who were deprived of all publique imployment, (as ministers, or schollars) by his declaration, Jan. 1. 1655.</title>
            <author>Gauden, John, 1605-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85861</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G365</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E765_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207143</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866214</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866214</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118479</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85861)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118479)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 117:E765[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A remonstrance presented to O.P. Feb. 4. 1655. By J.G. D.D. A son, servant, and supplicant for the Church of England: in behalf of many thousands his distressed brethren (ministers of the Gospel, and other good schollars) who were deprived of all publique imployment, (as ministers, or schollars) by his declaration, Jan. 1. 1655.</title>
                  <author>Gauden, John, 1605-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 26, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Milbourn for Andrew Crook, at the Green-Dragon in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659 [i.e. 1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J.G. = John Gauden; O.P. = Oliver Protector.</note>
                  <note>Final two pages = postscript.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 15.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118479:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PETITIONARY REMONSTRANCE, PRESENTED TO O. P. <hi>FEB.</hi> 4. 1655. By <hi>J.G. D.D.</hi> A Son, Servant, and Supplicant for the <hi>CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH</hi> of <hi>ENGLAND:</hi> In behalf of many thouſands his diſtreſſed Brethren (Miniſters of the Goſpel, and other good Schollars) who were deprived of all publique imployment, (as Miniſters, or Schollars) by His DECLARATION, <hi>JAN.</hi> 1. 1655.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 122.1.</hi>
               </bibl> For my Brethren and Companions ſakes.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 13.2.</hi>
               </bibl> Though I could remove Mountains, and have no chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I am nothing.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mark 9.41.</hi>
               </bibl> Whoſoever ſhall give you a cup of cold water to drink in my Name, becauſe ye belong to Chriſt, verily I ſay unto you, he ſhall not loſe his reward.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Milbourn</hi> for <hi>Andrew Crook,</hi> at the <hi>Green-Dragon</hi> in <hi>Pauls-Church-yard,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118479:2"/>
            <head>THE PUBLISHER TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>FInding by better judgements than my own, that this following Petitionary Remonſtrance, to his late Highneſſe <hi>O. P.</hi> (then in power) was not only a modeſt and charitable <hi>Addreſs,</hi> ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able at that time, and ſafe at all times; but alſo pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentially pious and politick; ſo as it may be of good uſe in theſe times; I have preſumed to make it publique; Not but I know, that it was at firſt written with an intent to conceale it from all eyes, but thoſe to which it was at firſt preſented, (which are now buried, as all humane glory will be, in duſt and darkneſſe) yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that, as a Jewel, it ſtill reteined its native luſture; and might well fit the dark, and dubious condition, wherein moſt Miniſters in <hi>England,</hi> are thought to ſtand (or rather to fall) as to their liberty and livelihood; beſide their reputation, and reſpect; All which ſeem to be at a very <hi>low</hi> ebb, but on a dangerous precipice, and downfal, If ſome men may have their will; I ſuppoſed this <hi>peice,</hi> might in no leſſe be acceptable, than ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to all <hi>ingenious</hi> Chriſtians, and <hi>worthy Readers;</hi> who ſtill preſerve any love, and reſpect to the <hi>flock of God,</hi> and the <hi>glory of our Iſrael:</hi> I mean the <hi>Reformed</hi> Religion, of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the faithul <hi>Miniſtery</hi> of it, to whom I profeſſe my ſelf a moſt affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate friend and ſervant.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:118479:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>§.</hi> Whoſe common dangers and diſadvantages, ought with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to invite them prudently and ſpeedily to compoſe their <hi>private differences,</hi> leaſt while they ſcramble, <hi>as boyes,</hi> for the <hi>nuts</hi> of petty opinions, and ſome formal ſhadows of Religion, they (and we) loſe the main ſubſtance, and grand <hi>eſſentials of it,</hi> not only as to <hi>holy</hi> diſcipline order <hi>and</hi> government, <hi>(which muſt firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin among Miniſters themſelves)</hi> but alſo as to <hi>true worſhip, ſound doctrine,</hi> and <hi>ſober reformation,</hi> which they cannot but ſee, and many of them confeſs, to be much upon the <hi>decline</hi> and <hi>abatement,</hi> both as to <hi>ſanctity</hi> and <hi>ſolemnity:</hi> That I mention not <hi>Miniſters</hi> own <hi>ſecular intereſts,</hi> as to <hi>honeſt ſubſiſtance,</hi> and <hi>civil reſpects,</hi> which no ingenuous men can well want, and no wiſe man will ſupinely neglect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>§.</hi> This is moſt certain, that <hi>Miniſters diviſions</hi> do mainly advance, as the peoples <hi>diſtractions,</hi> ſo their own diminution and <hi>deſtruction;</hi> for their <hi>factions</hi> and <hi>fewds</hi> among themſelves, ſerve only as <hi>rougher hones,</hi> or <hi>whetſtones,</hi> to ſet <hi>ſharper edges</hi> on the <hi>ſwords</hi> and <hi>ſythes</hi> of their <hi>enemies,</hi> whoſe deſolating and implacable ſpite, will never be ſtopped or reſiſted, unleſs <hi>grave</hi> and godly <hi>Miniſters,</hi> of all ſides, be ſo far bleſſed of God, as (firſt) to recover their reaſon and reputation, in point of <hi>piety</hi> and <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, prudence</hi> and <hi>charity,</hi> by <hi>mutual correſpondencies</hi> and cloſures, ſo as to <hi>concenter</hi> in ſome <hi>uniform</hi> way of <hi>Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> and <hi>Order:</hi> united, they would be as <hi>venerable,</hi> as, ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, they are <hi>contemptible,</hi> like <hi>figures</hi> or <hi>cyphers,</hi> they would ſignifie much in their <hi>conjunction,</hi> little or nothing in their <hi>ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>§.</hi> From hence (in the ſecond place) they would appear to the world, not only as petty <hi>Presbyters,</hi> or <hi>Predicants,</hi> ſingle and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, but as a grave and <hi>Venerable Society,</hi> and <hi>combination</hi> of learned and wiſe men, worthy to manage religious concernments, and to enjoy publique <hi>incouragements,</hi> from thoſe that may have at any time Supreme Power in their hands, who will alwayes have ſo much, either <hi>piety or policy</hi> in their hearts, as <hi>impartially</hi> to diſpenſe Juſtice and rewards to able, peaceable, and orderly Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, as well as to any other ſort of deſerving men, that are in any <hi>Civil or Military</hi> imployment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>§.</hi> Conſidering, that the <hi>Nation of England</hi> never owed to
<pb facs="tcp:118479:3"/>any <hi>calling</hi> of men, more, either of its <hi>happineſſe</hi> or <hi>miſery,</hi> than to its <hi>Clergy</hi> or <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> under whatever <hi>Laws</hi> or <hi>forms they may paſſe:</hi> Indeed they alwayes have had, and ever will have, great <hi>influence</hi> on the <hi>fate</hi> and <hi>fortunes</hi> of any people that are <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> whoſe <hi>conſciences</hi> firſt, then their eſtates, at laſt their peace and ſafety (publique as well as private) are ſo far, either <hi>maintained</hi> or <hi>undermined</hi> by their <hi>Miniſters,</hi> as theſe find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves either <hi>favoured</hi> and honored, or <hi>depreſſed</hi> and <hi>debaſed,</hi> being men, that commonly have not only a good <hi>opinion of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> but very quick reſentments of things, apt both for their <hi>pragmatique,</hi> and <hi>ſpeaking veine,</hi> to have a notable <hi>byaſs</hi> and <hi>ſtroke</hi> upon mens <hi>minds,</hi> and ſo upon <hi>publique affairs,</hi> by their <hi>tongues</hi> and <hi>pens,</hi> beſides their more <hi>ſolemn preachings</hi> and <hi>prayings,</hi> with a <hi>devout inſinuation</hi> into mens and womens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, among whom they have ſo much of civil and religious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>§.</hi> Hence it is, that <hi>poverty and deſpiciency</hi> caſt upon the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry,</hi> makes them either <hi>ſilly ſots,</hi> and abject <hi>ſlaves,</hi> or elſe ſo far unquiet, as they are ſenſible of, and <hi>diſſatisfied</hi> with their <hi>conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> And how (indeed) can ſuch men, as think themſelves fit to be publique <hi>Pilots of Religion,</hi> and <hi>Conducters of Souls</hi> to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, be much concerned in the civil peace or ſafety of that <hi>Ship,</hi> (or <hi>Commonwealth</hi>) (how rich ſoever it be) where they ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo pittifully <hi>imbarqued,</hi> and poorly entertained in it, that they may well hope for better <hi>prize</hi> and <hi>pillage</hi> in the <hi>common ſhipwrack,</hi> than for <hi>pay</hi> or profit, by any voyage that it makes, wherein they are imployed indeed as <hi>Predicants,</hi> but yet kept under as Mendicants, not permitted to have any joynt <hi>ſtock,</hi> or <hi>ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> either of honor, or eſtate conſiderable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>§.</hi> Therefore wiſe men conclude it undoubtedly beſt, in point of <hi>State-policy,</hi> either to have no able and learned <hi>Miniſters</hi> at all, whoſe education makes them men of <hi>parts</hi> and <hi>ſpirit;</hi> a project which will ſoon amount to no <hi>Religion</hi> at all, at leaſt no <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> and to be ſure, no <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> juſtly ſo called; for this (as times now are, full of <hi>Religious,</hi> as well as <hi>civil wars</hi>) muſt ever be <hi>ſtrongly guarded,</hi> and ſtoutly maintained by a Spiritual Militia of <hi>well-paid,</hi> and <hi>well-fed, well-learned,</hi> and <hi>well-arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> Miniſters, elſe <hi>London</hi> will ſoon run to <hi>Rome,</hi> and the <hi>Thames</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:118479:4"/>ſubmit to <hi>Tyber,</hi> which is the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by ſome men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>§.</hi> On the other ſide, it will be <hi>Policy,</hi> no leſs than <hi>Piety,</hi> to entertain ſuch able <hi>Schollars,</hi> and worthy <hi>Miniſters,</hi> ſo as becomes men of <hi>good learning, uſeful parts,</hi> and <hi>exemplary lives,</hi> in order to maintain the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> which is the intereſt of this Nation, both ſecular and ſpiritual, civil and conſcientious: To which I may juſtly add, that <hi>grateful reſpect</hi> which is due to the <hi>Sanctity</hi> and Majeſty of that <hi>God and Saviour,</hi> whom able Miniſters powerfully <hi>preach,</hi> and <hi>people ſincerely profeſs,</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying with them thoſe <hi>ineſtimable</hi> and <hi>eternal bleſſings,</hi> which are only to be had ordinarily by thoſe <hi>holy duties,</hi> which good Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters worthily perform; and thoſe <hi>Venerable Myſteries</hi> which they duly celebrate and diſpenſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>§.</hi> All which ſacred and grave <hi>concernments</hi> of Gods Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and <hi>mens Souls,</hi> your <hi>ignorant, mechanick,</hi> and <hi>hedge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creeping</hi> Teachers; your <hi>popular, poor,</hi> and <hi>Paraſitick Preachers;</hi> your <hi>under-bred</hi> and <hi>under-fed Orators;</hi> your <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually, illiterate, impudent, and ridiculous Praters, will infallibly <hi>proſtitute,</hi> not only to <hi>Jeſuitick jeers,</hi> and <hi>Romiſh deiſion,</hi> but to all peoples <hi>vilifyings.</hi> and <hi>contempts,</hi> who eaſily follow thoſe inbred principles, and impulſes tending to <hi>licentiouſneſſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſſe,</hi> or <hi>ſuperſtition,</hi> which makes all men (without Gods Grace) no leſs oppoſite to the true power of <hi>Preachers,</hi> (as <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritative Biſhops, and Paſtors of Souls</hi>) than to the <hi>Power of Preaching;</hi> that is, to the <hi>Power of Godlineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>§.</hi> The aim therefore of this <hi>Preface,</hi> (full of reſpect and love to that Holy Calling by which my Soul hath profited) is only to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade all able <hi>Schollars,</hi> and worthy <hi>Miniſters,</hi> of all ſides, to ſuch wiſe and Brotherly <hi>Agreements</hi> among themſelves, as may by joynt <hi>Counſels,</hi> moſt conduce to their own <hi>honor</hi> and <hi>ſafety,</hi> as well as the publique peace and ſatisfaction, leaſt all of them in their diſperſions, and mutual depreſsions (one after another) come to <hi>drink</hi> of that ſame <hi>bitter cup,</hi> which ſo many of their <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> lately did, in great meaſure, whoſe cauſe was ſo <hi>freely plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> by the <hi>Author</hi> of this Work, while many others with <hi>dumb</hi> and <hi>dry eyes</hi> looked on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>§.</hi> I paſsionately deprecate the like <hi>diſtreſſes</hi> falling on any thoſe <hi>Miniſters,</hi> who were either occaſioners, or <hi>pittileſs Spectators</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:118479:4"/>their own Brethrens ſore <hi>afflictions.</hi> The <hi>ambition</hi> of my prayer is, that all worthy <hi>Miniſters</hi> may not only in their private places demean themſelves, in all things, as become learned, pious, and prudent men: But further, that they may be ſo much favoured of God and man, as to have the freedome of publique <hi>Synods</hi> and <hi>Conventions,</hi> for their better underſtanding of each other in truth and love: In ſuch conſpicuities, no doubt, they will appear to all good Chriſtians of the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> every way worthy of all <hi>publique countenance</hi> and <hi>incouragement,</hi> that <hi>Chriſtian Magiſtrates</hi> may own and <hi>entertain</hi> them as <hi>Chriſtian Miniſters,</hi> ſubjects (indeed) as to Civil Power, in all things juſt and honeſt, yet ſtill as <hi>Chriſts Agents,</hi> and <hi>Gods Embaſſadors,</hi> ſent as from Heaven to treat with <hi>ſinful mortals,</hi> in order to their <hi>eternal life</hi> and <hi>peace,</hi> Under which names, (of publique <hi>Agents</hi> and <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors</hi>) all perſons are <hi>handſomely</hi> and <hi>honorably</hi> received, and uſed, by people not wholly <hi>barbarous,</hi> although they come but from <hi>petty Princes,</hi> and mean <hi>Seigniories,</hi> and (poſsibly) upon buſineſs of no great <hi>concernment,</hi> further than wonted <hi>forms</hi> and <hi>ceremonies</hi> of State, which have uſually more of the craft and <hi>policy</hi> of <hi>Spies,</hi> than of the <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>reality</hi> of <hi>friends.</hi> But the deſign of Miniſters is to promote that one thing neceſſary, the great and eternal intereſt of ſaving ſouls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>§.</hi> Till Chriſtianity ſeems a <hi>fable,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> be thought an <hi>Impoſtor,</hi> his ſacred <hi>Miniſtry</hi> and <hi>true Miniſters</hi> will be in requeſt among good Chriſtians, eſpecially if they would add to the certainty of their <hi>meſſage</hi> and Commiſsion, the order, unity, and authority of their Ordination or <hi>Miſſion,</hi> which would be much to their own Honor, and the peoples ſatisfaction, that we might know of whom we have and receive the Myſteries of Chriſts Kingdome. Indeed, by this means, they would every way render, not only their pains and perſons, but their Profeſsion and Calling, moſt conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Publique; redeeming themſelves by mutual advice and <hi>aſſiſtance,</hi> from <hi>plebeian ſoftneſſe,</hi> as well as <hi>ſervility:</hi> Their <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude</hi> makes them ſo fearful, and ſo <hi>ſervile,</hi> if they had not been <hi>ſcattered,</hi> they could not have been thus <hi>worried.</hi> And if ſome of them had not ſtooped ſo much as <hi>Camels</hi> to <hi>vulgar complian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> mean people had not ſo much got upon their <hi>backs,</hi> or <hi>load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them</hi> (as they have) a long time with <hi>poverty, reproach,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:118479:5"/>
               <hi>contempt,</hi> ſo far as in them lies: They will never be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, till they are <hi>unanimous</hi> and <hi>uniform,</hi> in the main of their <hi>Religion, Reformation,</hi> and <hi>Function,</hi> which I heartily pray for, as a principal <hi>foundation</hi> of their own, and all the <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons welfare,</hi> which deſerves not to be <hi>happy,</hi> while their able <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> are <hi>miſerable:</hi> Nor can it indeed be other than <hi>miſerable,</hi> till worthy Miniſters of the Goſpel are <hi>happily ſettled,</hi> and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hily <hi>treated.</hi> Farewel.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118479:5"/>
            <head>TO HIS HIGHNESSE OLIVER, Lord Protector, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ext to a juſt <hi>Zeal</hi> for Gods Glory,
<note place="margin">The Religious motives to this Addreſſe.</note> and a <hi>gratefull recognition</hi> of my Saviours ſufferings; the ſenſe I have of Gods undeſerved indulgence to my ſelf, and the Compaſſions I own for other mens <hi>Calamities:</hi> Theſe have put me upon this adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of preſenting your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> with this <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionary Remonſtrance;</hi> In which, having no confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of any particular <hi>Intereſt</hi> in your Highneſſes favour, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to ſuch an <hi>Interceſſion,</hi> I have yet taken upon me ſo much <hi>Pious preſumption,</hi> as to tender it to your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> in their Names, and for their ſakes, who are the great <hi>Preſervers,</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemers</hi> of Men.</p>
            <p>§. Which ſervice of Charity I may, and ought to performe with the more ingenuous freedome, becauſe I am not involved in the <hi>Diſtreſſe,</hi> as to my <hi>particular condition,</hi> which deſerves to be miſerable, if I had an Heart that could not be moved, or durſt not take the boldneſſe to move your <hi>Highneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſad occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> in behalf of many my <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Brethren;</hi> my <hi>Betters</hi> and <hi>Equals,</hi> learned, peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, pious, and induſtrious Miniſters, with other good <hi>Scholars,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118479:6"/>whom your Highneſſes late <hi>Thunder-bolt</hi> hath ſo ſtrucken and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, as they are filled with grief to an <hi>Horror,</hi> and with <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection</hi> to a <hi>Deſpair;</hi> (Paſſions (like Hell torments) not conceive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by any but thoſe, who are involved in the ſame gulf of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity!</hi>) while they not onely fear, but evidently ſee themſelves (with their <hi>neareſt</hi> and deareſt <hi>Relations</hi>) ſuddenly condemned by your <hi>Highneſs</hi>'s late <hi>Edict</hi> of <hi>Jan.</hi> 1. (after ſo many years ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings) to be for ever either ſadly <hi>indigent,</hi> or ſordidly <hi>imployed;</hi> or (which is worſe to ingenuous men) to be <hi>ſupinely idle,</hi> as having nothing left, or allowed them to do, deſerve or enjoy in any publique way agreeable to their liberal <hi>Education,</hi> and learned <hi>Abilities:</hi> Conſequently, little or nothing can be left them to feed, clothe, and comfortably maintain themſelves, and their Families; moſt of them being but <hi>poor men</hi> as to their <hi>temporal eſtates,</hi> (though many of their <hi>Souls are rich Mines</hi> of knowledge, grace, and all Vertue) having chiefly lived heretofore by Gods Bleſſing, and this Nations bounteous Reward upon their <hi>Learned Induſtry;</hi> in which conſiſteth the whole ſtock, and patrimony of moſt <hi>Miniſters</hi> and <hi>Scholars;</hi> whoſe trading for <hi>wiſdome</hi> commonly <hi>marrs</hi> their <hi>market</hi> for all other gain, further than what the Churches Patrimony, and the States Munificence <hi>may afford</hi> them.</p>
            <p>§.
<note place="margin">Compaſſion no Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</note> Whoſe <hi>Tragique terrors,</hi> and impending miſeries ſo imedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, and inevitably menacing them, I cannot but <hi>Remonſtrate</hi> with a charitable fervour, yet with all due <hi>reſpect</hi> to your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Not as hereby <hi>ſymboliſhing</hi> with, or abetting any of theſe my Brethren, in any wayes miſ-becoming Pious and Prudent men; but only as <hi>ſympathiſing</hi> with ſuch deſerving perſons in their <hi>undeſerved conſternations,</hi> which they conclude to be ſad fore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of ſuch <hi>dreadful diſtreſſes,</hi> as muſt needs drive them, and their whole Families upon the rocks and precipices of <hi>utter ruine;</hi> unleſs the <hi>mercy of God,</hi> by your <hi>Highneſſes Benignity,</hi> be pleaſed ſo to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe, as to preſerve them, and theirs from theſe <hi>multi-forme miſeries,</hi> which are in the face of Famine, and thoſe neceſſities which attend that <hi>extreme poverty,</hi> with which they are threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>§.
<note place="margin">Upon what account Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are thus afflicted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new.</note> All which cannot but be the more grievous to learned, grave, and <hi>ingenuous Miniſters,</hi> by how much they were now leſſe expected, or upon any <hi>new account,</hi> as they humbly conceive, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by them. As for the old ſcore of <hi>Malignity</hi> imputed to them, either (for their adherency to the <hi>Conſtitutions of the Church of England,</hi> or their <hi>Loyalty to their Soveraigne</hi>) they juſtly hoped; that the many difficulties already ſuſteined by them; the <hi>infinite diminutions,</hi> which (not in the <hi>way of Law,</hi> but of <hi>Armes</hi> and <hi>force</hi>)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118479:6"/>have exhauſted them. The <hi>Iliaedes</hi> of <hi>miſeries,</hi> which for many years have oppreſſed them upon that account, or <hi>Cauſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Their former great ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings upon the old account of Malignancy.</note> (in which they were not <hi>active,</hi> or <hi>militant,</hi> but onely <hi>paſſive,</hi> and <hi>conſtant,</hi> to the perſwaſions of their <hi>Conſciences;</hi>) which yet expoſed them to the <hi>ſpoiling of their goods,</hi> to the <hi>ſequeſtring</hi> of their Eſtates; to the loſſe of their Libraries, which were their Mines and Treaſuries; to the charge and ſqualor of <hi>Impriſonments;</hi> to long <hi>Abſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> from their neareſt Relations; or (upon their Releaſemen) to the ſad <hi>ſpectacles</hi> of their Families, and their own <hi>innumerable Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities,</hi> even to extremities of want. Horrors ſufficient (God knowes) to caſt ingenuous, and tender mindes into ſuch <hi>Agony's</hi> of dejection and deſpair, as nothing but an <hi>Angel</hi> from Heaven, or ſome ſpecial meaſure of Grace, was capable to preſerve them from <hi>curſing the day of their Birth,</hi> and the way of <hi>their Breeding;</hi> yea, from <hi>Blaſpheming God, and dying;</hi> as <hi>Jobs</hi> wife moſt unadvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly adviſed her afflicted Husband, when ſhe ſaw his Integrity was no ſecurity from extreme, and undeſerved miſeries.</p>
            <p>§.
<note place="margin">Their former imputed faults may ſeeme expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by their paſt afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> Thoſe <hi>innumerable diſtreſſes</hi> which have formerly preſſed upon moſt of theſe Miniſters (ever ſince they applyed themſelves to that <hi>cauſe,</hi> or <hi>croſſe</hi> rather, on which they have for ſome years paſt been <hi>nailed,</hi> and <hi>crucified</hi>) thoſe they hoped might (even in the rigour, and <hi>extremity of juſtice</hi>) have ſufficed to have <hi>expiated</hi> any former Offences, or Jealouſies taken up againſt them, during the heat of the late unhappy Warre; which made them <hi>criminals,</hi> or guilty rather by prejudices, providences, and preventions, than by any <hi>depravedneſſe</hi> of mindes, or <hi>immorality</hi> of manners ever proved againſt them.</p>
            <p>§. What ever juſt blame,
<note place="margin">Their Plea as to the point of Malignancy imputed to them.</note> or ſiniſter cenſure <hi>they</hi> had thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred upon thoſe <hi>former ſeores;</hi> yet they preſumed, ſince their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment had been greater than <hi>their iniquity,</hi> all would now in the <hi>coole</hi> of the day have been looked upon as many wayes <hi>venial,</hi> and <hi>excuſable</hi> in them. Conſidering,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the cauſe whereto they adhered,
<note n="1" place="margin">In their Conſciences.</note> and for which they ſuffered, was adopted by them without any <hi>perverſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> or ſiniſter ends: onely following <hi>(bona fide)</hi> that <hi>light of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> which ſeemed to them moſt clearly to ſhine from <hi>Gods Word,</hi> from the practice of Primitive Chriſtians, and the Lawes of the Land: All which taught them <hi>Loyalty,</hi> as a part of Chriſtian <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>non-reſiſtence</hi> of lawfull <hi>Soveraigne Power,</hi> as an <hi>indiſpenſable duty</hi> of Chriſtian ſubjects; only they had not been Catechiſed in ſuch Salvoes, and State-diſtinctions as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards were found out by other men, who ſeemed no leſſe ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſolicitous for their own Conſciences.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note n="2" place="margin">As to their patience, and ſilence.</note> Since God ſaw fit to confute their <hi>ſecular confidences
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118479:7"/>of any cauſe;</hi> and to teach them higher wiſdome <hi>by afflictions,</hi> (which in the juſteſt cauſe of men can never be injuſt, as from the hand of God) they have onely behaved themſelves, as humble, and <hi>ſilent ſufferers;</hi> patiently enduring: and <hi>devoutly undone:</hi> Not <hi>bitterly querulous;</hi> nor <hi>pragmatically perturbing the publique tranquillity;</hi> living in wayes many of them, (though very able and ample men) as little to be envyed, as much to be pittied; taking great <hi>pains</hi> for ſmall <hi>gain,</hi> contented with ſuch poor <hi>pittances,</hi> as are the refuſe of others, lately their <hi>inferiours,</hi> but now poſſeſſed of their livings; out of which they hardly allow to their ſequeſtred Brethren their miſerable Fifts. Only their <hi>humility and content</hi> made every <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition a competency;</hi> yea they <hi>rejoyced</hi> in their <hi>obſcurity,</hi> as hoping it was <hi>accompanied,</hi> with leſſe <hi>envy</hi> and more <hi>ſafety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§.
<note place="margin">Their Plea for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the Act of Oblivion.</note> Yet after all theſe <hi>meritorius miſeries,</hi> ſo <hi>modeſtly endured;</hi> after the noiſes and tumult of <hi>warr</hi> ſo much allayed: after an ACT of OBLIVION, happily paſſed (which they ſay owed much to your Highneſs's <hi>equanimity</hi> and <hi>policy</hi>) after other men of all ſorts, have been permitted to enjoy the benefit of <hi>Compoſition</hi> and <hi>reſtitution</hi> to their eſtates; except only <hi>Miniſters</hi> to their <hi>Eccleſiaſtical livings;</hi> (Their Sequeſtrations proving Deprivations for the moſt part: and their Purgatory is become an Hell.) After the <hi>Storme</hi> was well over, and the <hi>bitterneſſe of death</hi> ſeemed paſt; after theſe poor Miniſters had gained ſome little <hi>planck</hi> or rafter, poſſiblely a little refuſe living: or a <hi>Curateſhip,</hi> or a <hi>School;</hi> or a <hi>Lecture,</hi> or ſome Chaplains place in a Gentlemans houſe, by which to ſave themſelves from utter <hi>ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack</hi> and <hi>ſinking;</hi> yet ſtill (beyond any other ranck of men, of the ſame perſwaſions) they are now alarumed a freſh; expoſed to new <hi>conflictings</hi> with <hi>that armed man;</hi> forced to undergo again, <hi>the heat and burthen of the day,</hi> as to mans wrath, and jealouſly; whoſe very mercys may ſeem <hi>cruelty,</hi> and their ſparing of their lives thus long, great <hi>ſeverities;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Their Diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. more bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than Death.</note> while they are now brought, not to the <hi>Tarpeian Rock,</hi> whence by a ſudden <hi>principitation,</hi> an end might be put to all their miſeries, with their lives; But like <hi>Prometheus,</hi> they are bound alive with fatal <hi>Chains</hi> to the mountain <hi>Caucaſus:</hi> where condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be idle, the vulture of famine, &amp; all worldly calamities muſt be ever <hi>preying</hi> upon the bowels of themſelves, their <hi>Wives</hi> and <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> being only ſuffered to ſurvive their <hi>miſeries,</hi> as men hung a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live in <hi>Chaines,</hi> and forced with their relations either to <hi>begge, ſteal,</hi> or <hi>ſtarve.</hi> § Thus, thus, after the voyce of peace, was again <hi>heard</hi> in the land, and every man had begun to gather up his <hi>affairs,</hi> from the ſcattering of warr: yet now are theſe poor men, Sequeſtred <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and other ejected Scholars, condemned to be utterly caſt out of all as <hi>unſavory</hi> ſalt, by a moſt ſevere <hi>abdication,</hi> and as it were <hi>poſtliminious proſcription,</hi> forbidding any man to receive them
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118479:7"/>by any hoſpitable or charitable <hi>reception,</hi> ſo as to <hi>officiate,</hi> and merit any ſubſiſtence in their callings, either as <hi>Preachers,</hi> or <hi>Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> though it be but of children in a Blefry, or private Family.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Tragedy</hi> (my Lord) ſo <hi>Tragical</hi> in the firſt aſpect of it,
<note place="margin">The dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of the Tragedy, which threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens them.</note> and ſo killing in the letter, that in earneſt if (as a deſolating ſtorme) it ſhould be <hi>rigorouſly</hi> executed, upon ſo many learned and Godly men, together with the many modeſt <hi>Matrones</hi> their Wives, and their many hopefull, as well as harmeleſſe children, it is not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to expreſſe the <hi>bitter cryes,</hi> and ſad <hi>lamentations,</hi> with which it will fill the land, and all mens Hearts, that have any thing <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> or <hi>humane</hi> in them.</p>
            <p>§ So that if your Highneſs ſhould be inexorable, and unremiſſive, as one that neither <hi>hears</hi> nor <hi>regards,</hi> the <hi>cryes</hi> of ſo many <hi>poore Creatures:</hi> If their <hi>teares flowing night and day,</hi> ſhould only fall upon <hi>flints</hi> and nether-<hi>milſtones,</hi> as to other mens hearts, (where <hi>iniquity abounding,
<note place="margin">Their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the Divine Mercy.</note> charity muſt needs grow cold</hi>) there will be no way left but to <hi>fly to God;</hi> Their <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>bitter</hi> complaints, will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly peirce the <hi>Heavens;</hi> and move his compaſſion, who is a lover of Man-kind, both in grace, and nature; whom nothing more provoke to hear the Prayers of the Oppreſſed then the deafneſſe of men: Humane (or rather unhumane) <hi>cruelties</hi> by a kind of <hi>Antipathy</hi> or <hi>repercuſſion</hi> excite the divine <hi>mercies,</hi> as things that meet with the hardeſt <hi>repulſe,</hi> and reſiſtances downwards, do uſually make the greateſt <hi>rebounde</hi> and aſcent <hi>upwards,</hi> ſo do the cryes of the deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and greatly afflicted, when not regarded by men in Power.</p>
            <p>§. Be pleaſed to know,
<note place="margin">Their truſt in God for Grace.</note> that the Faith of theſe good men (who no doubt are dear and precious to God as his Jewels) is yet ſo much above <hi>their feares, and ſufferings</hi> as to believe that <hi>the Lords Eare</hi> is not heavy, that he cannot heare, nor his <hi>hand ſhortned,</hi> that he will not helpe thoſe who truſt in him, and cry unto him in the <hi>bitterneſs of their ſouls:</hi> though the <hi>Vine, and Olive, and Fig-tree</hi> fail them, yet God will not: though the arme of fleſhly power, be either withered and ſhrunck; or <hi>ſireched</hi> out againſt them, and lie heavy upon them, yet God will not utterly forſake thoſe, whoſe hearts are not onely upright before him: but endued by him, with many <hi>excellent,</hi> and ſpeciall gifts, uſefull for his glory, and his Churches good; beſides thoſe many Chriſtian graces, which are dayly increaſed, as well as excerciſed by ſuch ſore <hi>afflictions,</hi> and fiery trials; wherein they know as the Lord can <hi>purify them,</hi> ſo he can <hi>protect</hi> them, either from them, or in the midſt of them, as he did the <hi>Three Children</hi> when they were caſt into the <hi>Furnance</hi> ſeven times hotter then ordinary; he can and will ſave their precious Souls though the <hi>dunghill</hi> be their <hi>Death bed;</hi> as is now threatned to many of theſe poor, but <hi>Pious</hi> men.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118479:8"/>
            <p>§ Yet we know the Lord can ſtir up ſome mercifull <hi>Obediahs</hi> to feed theſe diſtreſſed <hi>Prophets</hi> in their <hi>caves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">For wayes of Relief.</note> and <hi>Obſcurities;</hi> and if ſuch <hi>mercifull men be periſhed</hi> from <hi>the earth,</hi> either for want of <hi>ability,</hi> or heroick <hi>charity,</hi> yet there may be ſome mercifull ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens (men otherwiſe <hi>rapacious</hi> and <hi>tenacious</hi> enough) who ſhall feed theſe <hi>hungry Elias</hi>'s, to the juſt reproach of thoſe men, who being great pretenders to <hi>Godlyneſs,</hi> and <hi>reformation,</hi> (the truth of which is inſeparable from <hi>charity, reliefe of the poor,</hi> and releaſing the oppreſſed) do (yet) deny <hi>bread to men of underſtanding;</hi> and <hi>inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous imployment</hi> to perſons of ſuch holy, and honeſt, and uſefull induſtry; and this in a land of plenty, not only for bodily food, but alſo for ſpirituall worke, where the <hi>harvei</hi> of ſouls is great and able <hi>labourers</hi> not too many; good Scholars being as neceſſary as Souldiers: and faithfull Miniſters, no leſſe deſerving their <hi>Salaries</hi> than <hi>Military</hi> men; Theſe will have their wages though they do not much work; the other would be glad to have leave to work, that they might deſerve and enjoy their wages.</p>
            <p>§ But becauſe we <hi>muſt not tempt</hi> God by expectance of <hi>miraculous reliefes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to his Highneſſes Clemency.</note> till we have tryed all wayes of ordinary providence, and find them obſtructed; I have thought it my duty, to uſe this moſt <hi>probable meanes</hi> to obteine your <hi>Highneſſes</hi> favour, toward theſe worthy men; that they may have <hi>leave</hi> to <hi>tread out the corne,</hi> without having their <hi>mouths thus muzled;</hi> that they may, as well <hi>Preach,</hi> as live <hi>Chriſt crucified,</hi> ſhewing others the <hi>benefit</hi> of his Croſſe, as well as <hi>bearing</hi> it themſelves; That they and theirs may not be ſtarved for want of bodily Food, while they are able, and willing to diſpenſe the Bread of Heaven, and food of Souls, which is the glorious Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt: being Perſons of no <hi>ſcandalous convictions,</hi> either for <hi>inabilities,</hi> or <hi>immorali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties:</hi> Having no other imputation on them, but onely ſome State-jealouſies, and Political-Diſputes. In which, although they may poſſibly be ſtill leſſe ſatisfied in their Judgements and Conſciences; yet they know how with prudence to be <hi>ſilent,</hi> and with <hi>peaceableneſſe</hi> to live in all <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> and <hi>Honeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For ſuch men,
<note place="margin">Plea for ſuch worthy men, preſumed not unacceptable to his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> and Miniſters, why ſhould I be afraid, by a <hi>Charitable,</hi> and <hi>in-offenſive importunity,</hi> to ſolicite either your Highneſſes <hi>Clemency,</hi> (if they may have ſeemed heretofore to deſerve ſuch multiplied and renewed ſeverities) or <hi>your Equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity and Juſtice?</hi> if they never have, nor do deſerve ſo hard meaſure as this return both of their ſinne and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, after they once had publique Pardon, and never ſince Offended. This I do with the more courage, and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, becauſe I well conſider how bold and welcome we <hi>poor
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118479:8"/>ſinfull</hi> wretches are to the <hi>Throne of Gods Grace,</hi> when we bring no other plea for Mercy, (as from our ſelves) but onely the ſenſe of <hi>our miſeries;</hi> the <hi>conſcience</hi> of our ſins, and the <hi>confeſſion</hi> of our unworthineſſe.</p>
            <p>§. Nor are the timorous <hi>reſerves,</hi> or over cautious,
<note place="margin">The cautions ſilence of many, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of theſe Miniſters.</note> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable coſtiveneſſe</hi> of other men, any <hi>damp</hi> or <hi>remora,</hi> but rather a <hi>ſpurr,</hi> and <hi>impulſe</hi> to me. I ſee how many of all ſorts dayly paſse by the <hi>diſtreſſed Miniſters</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> as the <hi>Levite, Prieſt and Phariſee</hi> did by the <hi>wounded man, unconcerned:</hi> afraid to have any regard to them, or any <hi>compaſſion</hi> for them; what their charity dares onely <hi>whiſper</hi> to themſelves; or, it may be, with ſome <hi>hard ſpeeches,</hi> and odious reflections, jealouſly ſuggeſt <hi>to your Highneſſe</hi> that have I undertaken, by Gods help, <hi>freely,</hi> and <hi>fully,</hi> to <hi>repreſent</hi> to <hi>You,</hi> that ſo <hi>your Highneſſe</hi> may not be ignorant, nor remorſeleſſe as to their <hi>calamitous</hi> condition; which is like to be ſuch, that of <hi>all Men,</hi> they are indeed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to be the moſt <hi>miſerable</hi> in this world; if the want of all things can make thoſe miſerable, who want not the continual feaſt of a <hi>good Conſcience,</hi> and the ſupport of Gods Spirit to be patient.</p>
            <p>§. But, becauſe I know that great <hi>Statiſts,</hi> and wiſe <hi>Polititians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Two Reaſons of State con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, as grounds of the Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt Miniſters.</note> do not lightly apply ſo publique, and ſharp <hi>ſeverities</hi> in the method of Government, but either they aime at, Firſt, exemplary <hi>puniſhing</hi> former Offences: Or, ſecondly, at preventing <hi>future Inſolencies,</hi> which may endanger <hi>publique ſafety:</hi> (For <hi>private Feuds,</hi> and <hi>perſonal deſpights,</hi> or revenges upon any men, that are <hi>ſubject</hi> to their <hi>power,</hi> are <hi>impotencies,</hi> or <hi>paſſions,</hi> moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of great and valiant <hi>Spirits,</hi> and not incident to them, becauſe much below them.) §. Give me leave to <hi>Remonſtrate to your Highneſſe,</hi> That the exerciſe of ſuch <hi>Charity, Clemency,</hi> and <hi>Equanimity,</hi> as is deſired by me, for ſuch worthy Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and other <hi>Scholars,</hi> can no way either, Firſt, abate that <hi>Prudent Juſtice,</hi> which muſt puniſh <hi>Offenders,</hi> to preſerve the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent in peace: Nor ſecondly, can it <hi>incourage,</hi> for the future, ſuch <hi>licentiouſneſſe,</hi> or <hi>preſumption,</hi> as may any way endanger that publique tranquillity which your Highneſſe profeſſed to me was your <hi>impartial,</hi> and <hi>higheſt deſigne</hi> in <hi>Government,</hi> in which all honeſt men of all Principles, and Perſwaſions might enjoy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in peace.</p>
            <p>§. Firſt, As to the firſt point of <hi>punitive State-policy;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Firſt, as to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitive Juſtice for paſt Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conceive it was not ſo much an Act of <hi>Juſtice and Legality.</hi> as of <hi>Military caution,</hi> and <hi>prevention,</hi> while the <hi>Intereſt of Parties</hi> were ſadly divided in Warre; which at firſt inflicted ſo great loſſes and reſtraints, as upon others, ſo upon many <hi>Learned,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118479:9"/>Grave,</hi> and godly <hi>Miniſters;</hi> not as <hi>Penalties,</hi> but <hi>Securities.</hi> And certainly, thoſe principles, or perſwaſions, which firſt lead them to undergo ſo many Miſeries, by the <hi>improſperity</hi> of that <hi>Cauſe,</hi> to which they choſe to adhere, (holding themſelves ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged thereto in Conſcience by the Lawes of God and Man;) theſe can in no Juſtice <hi>of God or Man,</hi> deſerve to be alwayes ſo ſorely puniſhed. However (poſſibly) in reaſon of State, it might for a time be rather neceſſary, than juſt, that they ſhould be reſtrained, or weakned, <hi>flagrante bello;</hi> during the hot fits, and Paroxyſms of war, not <hi>quia nocuerunt,</hi> but <hi>ne nocere poſſint.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§.
<note place="margin">Paſt Offences more than ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished.</note> Yet when this <hi>Rivalry,</hi> jealouſie, and <hi>conteſt</hi> by Armes was once decided, and publique Oppoſitions were reduced to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Subjections, certainly ſuch as were at firſt ſufferers onely by way of caution, and prevention, do not want very juſt Pleas now for their liberty, and preſent <hi>indemnitie,</hi> notwithſtanding their ſuppoſed <hi>Conſtancy</hi> to their former <hi>Principles:</hi> of which, as no wiſe man is concerned to be curiouſly inquiſitive, ſo they cannot be <hi>injurious</hi> to any <hi>publique</hi> Power, and Peace, ſo long as they are modeſtly <hi>ſmothered,</hi> and <hi>in-offenſively ſilenced</hi> in their own Breſts or Conſciences, whoſe <hi>Dictates,</hi> your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> knows, are not under any mans <hi>Empire:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Whether mens private Perſwaſions are to be made pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> The ableſt men cannot change their <hi>Opinions</hi> when they will, nor will honeſt men pretend a <hi>Change</hi> where is none. Since then their former Sufferings were made uſe of for the <hi>ſecurity</hi> of that ſide, which now prevailes ſufficiently over them, as to the outward man. Since their preſent Conſtancy proceeds not from Factious pertinacy, (which is ſoon either ſubdued, or ſoftned by ſufferings) but onely from <hi>Conſciencious Integrity,</hi> which is, in Wiſe, and Good men, as a Diamond, unmalleable and invincible. Laſtly, ſince this is ſo modeſtly carried, as no way either <hi>invades,</hi> or <hi>affronts</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent Power, or publique <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Safety.</hi> Surely ſuch men may well appear rather the <hi>Objects</hi> of juſt <hi>Indulgence</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,</hi> than of any further <hi>renewed rigours,</hi> and endleſſe coer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions; eſpecially ſince their Principles kept private, (as they are) can do no hurt; and their Miniſterial abilities being made publique, may do <hi>much good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ Adde to this;
<note place="margin">His Highneſſe declared ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, as to Liberty of Conſcience.</note> what your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> hath highly pretended to, and much ſought to gaine <hi>beliefe in from the World;</hi> That no <hi>man</hi> or <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> is more <hi>indulgent</hi> to reall liberty of <hi>conſcience;</hi> none more tender of making rude <hi>Scrutinies</hi> into <hi>mens hearts,</hi> (which are Gods <hi>Prorogative</hi> and <hi>reſerve</hi>) or of laying either rigid <hi>impoſitions</hi> upon mens <hi>Conſciences,</hi> or <hi>penaltys</hi> on their opinions; when their <hi>Converſation</hi> is ſuch, as becometh the <hi>Goſpell</hi> and our Lawes; neither <hi>impious</hi> nor <hi>injurious,</hi> neither <hi>idle</hi> nor <hi>Pragmatick.</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:118479:9"/>All which being granted, I cannot under favour ſee how it can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſt with your <hi>Highneſſes</hi> many other <hi>Declarations,</hi> and <hi>Profeſſions,</hi> to preſerve rational and <hi>Religious</hi> liberty <hi>unviolated.</hi> How then (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you) ſhould the conſtancy of theſe mens private <hi>perſwaſions,</hi> joyned with honeſty, and innocency of life, in any equity, render them ſo burthenſome, and intolerable to the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> as to exclude them for ever, from all civil, and <hi>Sacred Induſtry,</hi> in ſuch wayes of honeſt ſubſiſtence, as are ſutable to their <hi>education,</hi> and <hi>abilityes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ Who doubts, but that in civill <hi>addictions,</hi> and <hi>adherences,</hi>
               <note place="margin">His Highneſſe approving of mens conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to their Principles in his own Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt.</note> even your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> doth paſſionately deſire, and highly approve ſuch <hi>ſervants, ſubjects, friends,</hi> and <hi>followers,</hi> who are not upon ſiniſter, but ſincere reſpects, ſo devoted to your Safety, Honor, Power, and Intereſt, that they will not eaſily ſuffer themſelves to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from them, whereto they once have <hi>applied</hi> themſelves, not more with prudence, (which will onely hold in the <hi>Summer,</hi> and <hi>proſperity</hi> of your <hi>affairs,</hi> and <hi>family</hi>) than with <hi>conſcience, love,</hi> and <hi>gratitude:</hi> which will laſt in <hi>Winter</hi> and adverſity; as the life and ſap of <hi>Trees,</hi> doth when their leaves are faln; That vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue which is commendable in your <hi>Highneſſes</hi> caſe, cannot be blameable in anothers, though an enemy, becauſe it is a virtue.
<note place="margin">The Antiqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or obſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lete Cauſes of many Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</note>
            </p>
            <p>§ Nor is it to be forgotten, as to the examining, of the point of <hi>Juſtice</hi> in many excellent <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and other Scholars paſt <hi>ſufferings;</hi> That long before the ſcene of our <hi>civill affaires</hi> was thus altered, and ſetled, as now it is, under your <hi>Highneſſes Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> many of them were <hi>Silenced, Sequeſtred,</hi> and <hi>Ejected,</hi> out of their Livings, preferments, and Fellowſhips, meerly upon the ſcore, of I know not what, Occaſionall Covenants, new <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>owes,</hi> and State <hi>Engagements;</hi> which were but temporary Stratagems; ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuch various, and Particular Intereſts, as in their times were ſometimes on foot, and prevalent in their partyes and deſignes, All which having been long ſince juſtly <hi>antiquated,</hi> and <hi>aboliſhed,</hi> as to their ſecular virtue, and civill <hi>influence;</hi> it were great pity, they ſhould ſtill continue their deſtructive power, upon any good <hi>mens conſciences,</hi> Eſtates or Libertyes: as <hi>Comets</hi> are thought to do their <hi>malignancy,</hi> long after they are vaniſhed, and diſ-ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear: What juſtice can there be, that men ſhould continue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>penaltyes,</hi> when the partiall <hi>cauſes,</hi> or temporary occaſions, of their <hi>ſufferings,</hi> are quite ceaſed, and ſuppreſſed; nor did they ſuffer at firſt upon any morall, but onely politick <hi>conſiderations,</hi> as they were then preſented, by ſeverall Acters on the Engliſh Stage.</p>
            <p>Now the Lawes, both of <hi>Tragedies,</hi> and <hi>Comedies</hi> do permit that thoſe Actors, which in one ſcene, may ſeem judged, beaten,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118479:10"/>bound and killed, may in another act returne to be free, and in favour, according as the viciſſitudes of humane affaires, doe variouſly entertaine this life of man.</p>
            <p>§ If it be objected,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Objection, as to ſome Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters unquiet carriage Anſwered.</note> (to make all Miniſters, of that unſucceſfull adherency, ſeeme dangerous, and odious,) that ſome of them enjoying common <hi>freedom,</hi> and <hi>protection</hi> under your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> Government; have yet behaved themſelves other wayes, then became <hi>pious, peaceable,</hi> and <hi>prudent men,</hi> under power: yea, and contrary to that <hi>wiſdome,</hi> which <hi>affliction</hi> ſhould have taught them, in reference to both publique, and private peace; Yet no <hi>juſtice</hi> will permit, that ſome mens <hi>pragmatick petulancie,</hi> (who may poſſibly have more breath of paſſion in their ſailes, then balaſt of <hi>diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in the hold of their <hi>judgements,</hi>) ſhould be imputed to all men, of that <hi>learned Tribe;</hi> who may be of the ſame <hi>perſwaſion,</hi> but of far more prudence, and moderation.</p>
            <p>§ Nothing ſeemes harder meaſure,
<note place="margin">No Juſtice will puniſh many inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents for a few nocents.</note> and remoter from Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Juſtice, than for a few mens ſakes, (who may be infected with the <hi>itch,</hi> or <hi>leproſy,</hi> of impatient, and turbulent ſpirits for which they deſerve to be confined, till they are healed) to ſhut up all others, who were not at all infected with, or are cured of their diſeaſes; It is great pity, ſome mens <hi>inordinate</hi> activity, ſhould condemne others, to utter idleneſſe; and exclude ſuch able men even from thoſe mean imployments, (as to the emolument) to which they have cheerfully condeſcended, (ſince the <hi>frowns,</hi> and <hi>burden</hi> of the times, have greatly depreſſed them) in order to maintaine themſelves, and their familyes: which muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, if theſe may do nothing, for which they are apt, and proper.</p>
            <p>§ And ſince all proportions of both <hi>divine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Why Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished more than any men of the ſame Principles.</note> and <hi>humane</hi> juſtice do aſſure us, that thoſe opinions or perſwaſions, by which no private advantages are obteined, nor publique dangers threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, cannot be ſuch a plague, diſeaſe, or <hi>Gangrene,</hi> as are onely to becured, by theſe diſpiritings, and <hi>exhauſtings,</hi> which muſt needs follow extreme idleneſſe, and <hi>indigence;</hi> wiſe men cannot ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admire, what Councel or deſigne, puts your <hi>Highneſs</hi> upon execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe high ſeverities, only upon men of <hi>literature;</hi> Miniſters; &amp; other Scholars; denying them all ſuch ingenious <hi>libertyes</hi> to ſubſiſt, by their honeſt callings; which yet are granted fully &amp; freely to all other men; even the meaneſt <hi>tradeſmen,</hi> and <hi>mechanicks;</hi> who are of the ſame principles, and prone to be much more active in <hi>aſſerting</hi> them; and the wonder is the greater, becauſe your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> hath in my hearing as well as many others profeſſed, an impartiall value, of all able and good <hi>Miniſters;</hi> much commending ſome of the Epiſcopall way; yea, and almoſt preferring them, for their Graces and Gifts.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:118479:10"/>
            <p>Laſtly, becauſe your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> is pleaſed to own your ſelfe, not onely as <hi>Protector</hi> in generall; but as the ſpeciall <hi>Patrone</hi> of both the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> and in them of all good Literature, and Scholars, by being <hi>Chancellour</hi> of one of them, greater degree of favour may be hoped.</p>
            <p>§ I profeſſe to plead for no <hi>Miniſters,</hi> or <hi>Scholars,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plea for Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, as to their Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes.</note> that are ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalouſly <hi>criminous,</hi> or morally noxious; ſuch I beleive and hope few of theſe men are, who now fall under the milſtone of your <hi>Highneſſes</hi> late <hi>Declaration,</hi> which muſt needs grinde them to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; If it excecute what it threatens.</p>
            <p>§ But if the moſt of them were perſons, leſſe <hi>commendable;</hi> or for ſome <hi>miſdemenors,</hi> juſtly blamable, yea, and by law puniſhable; yet ſtill the very <hi>multitude</hi> of them, is no ſmall <hi>Plea;</hi> If not for totall <hi>impunity,</hi> yet for ſuch <hi>clemency,</hi> as may not ſeeme an outrage of <hi>ſeverity,</hi> and <hi>extremity</hi> of <hi>juſtice:</hi> what is more uſual in civill and Chriſtian States, than to ſuffer the edge of Juſtice to be <hi>blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> and the ſtroke of it <hi>defeated,</hi> rather then over-ſharply executed againſt the many Crouds: of <hi>offenders</hi> though they cannot oppoſe the <hi>ſiroakes of juſtice</hi> by force, yet they do as it were <hi>ſmother,</hi> and oppreſſe them; pinioning the armes even of juſt power with the <hi>cords</hi> of a man; the ſofter ſenſe of <hi>humanity;</hi> and, which is more, of <hi>Chriſtian pity;</hi> we find our bleſſed Saviour had more then once <hi>compaſſion</hi> on the <hi>multitude;</hi> not onely as <hi>neceſſitous,</hi> but as <hi>numerous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ Both which <hi>number,</hi> and <hi>neceſſity, multitude</hi> and <hi>miſery,</hi> do here ſo meet together, in the Objects of my Plea, and <hi>Petition,</hi> preſented before your <hi>Highneſſe,</hi> that your eye could not but affect your heart, if you could at one view, behold the great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities, and <hi>deplorable companies,</hi> of <hi>venerable Miniſters,</hi> and other <hi>ingenious Scholars,</hi> together with their <hi>dependances,</hi> and <hi>relations,</hi> (as <hi>wives, children, ſervants,</hi> and <hi>neceſſitous kindred</hi>) all which do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely dread, and earneſtly deprecate thoſe <hi>miſeryes,</hi> which hang over their heads; if the <hi>Fathers</hi> or cheif of their <hi>Families,</hi> be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to work in their callings; which is to forbid them all to eat or to live, at leaſt <hi>honeſtly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ I am confident ſo <hi>rufull a ſpectacle,</hi> (even amidſt the <hi>pomp,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſad ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and their Families, who are many thouſands ready to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish.</note> and <hi>ſplendor</hi> of your court) would more move your <hi>Highneſſe,</hi> to <hi>compaſſionate</hi> them, than the proſpect of <hi>Xerxes</hi> his <hi>Army</hi> did that <hi>Great King,</hi> when he wept to think how a few <hi>years</hi> would <hi>moulder</hi> to duſt ſo vaſt a number of valiant men; for theſe laſt muſt periſh by the Common Law, and inevitable fate of <hi>mortality;</hi> but thoſe many and good men, for whom I am bold to intercede, muſt it ſeemes be undone, and die meerely by their arbitrary <hi>neceſſityes,</hi> to which your <hi>Highneſſes Declaration</hi> onely doth drive, and condemne them.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:118479:11"/>
            <p>§ And which way, I beſeech your <hi>Highneſſe,</hi> without a miracle can theſe men by any unwonted induſtry, get <hi>livelyhood</hi> for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and their <hi>families!</hi> whoſe number cannot amount to leſſe then, <hi>Twenty</hi> or <hi>Thirty</hi> thouſand Soules; conſidering, that above <hi>halfe</hi> of the <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and <hi>Scholars,</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> have been, upon one <hi>account</hi> or <hi>other,</hi> Sequeſtred from their livings, (which are above Nine Thouſand) beſides Fellowſhips, or Free-Schooles; many other alſo have been wholy deprived of their <hi>Prebendaryes, Denaryes, Biſhopricks,</hi> and <hi>Higheſt Dignityes.</hi> in the <hi>Church;</hi> who upon the firſt Figure, or Head, cannot be leſſe then <hi>Six,</hi> or <hi>Seaven</hi> thouſand perſons; to each of which if we adde <hi>but four more,</hi> (which is but a ſmall Family or retinue) they cannot but exceed the proportion I have <hi>calculated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ And here,
<note place="margin">Plea from his Highneſſes conjugal, and paternal ſenſe.</note> my <hi>Lord,</hi> being your ſelfe reputed both a loving <hi>Husband,</hi> and a tender <hi>Father,</hi> I cannot but believe, that you are (as well as I am) extremely ſenſible of theſe <hi>conjugal,</hi> and <hi>peternal remorſes,</hi> which gnaw the very <hi>bowels,</hi> and pierce the Souls of all <hi>ingenuous</hi> men in behalf of their neareſt, and deareſt <hi>Relations;</hi> when they ſhall ſee theſe involved in the ſame <hi>calamityes</hi> with themſelves; and for their ſakes, to drinke as deep of the bitter cup, as their chiefes or principals; A Gracious Chriſtian may with gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>courage</hi> encounter his own death, as concluſive of his own <hi>miſeries,</hi> and his enemies malice: but who can endure to be ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of thoſe <hi>lingring torments,</hi> wherewith <hi>famine</hi> muſt kill, their <hi>Wives, and Children; Hagar</hi> went away, that ſhe might not be a ſad ſpectatrix of her Son <hi>Iſmaels</hi> death for want of <hi>Food.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ As the Laws of humanity teach us to abhor ſuch Dreadful <hi>Severityes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">God abhors dreadful ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities on the innocent, and the nocent that are nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous.</note> falling upon our <hi>Relations;</hi> ſo the God of Mercy would have them avoided in the juſteſt executions; that not the <hi>Children,</hi> and ſo not the <hi>Wives,</hi> ſhould beare the iniquity of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> or Husbands; yea Gods compaſſion pleaded againſt the <hi>paſſion,</hi> and <hi>peeviſhneſſe</hi> of <hi>Jonah</hi> for his ſparing <hi>Niniveh,</hi> (though he had denounced his wrath, and limited a day for protracting the <hi>Execution</hi>) even from the many Innocent <hi>Children,</hi> that were in that City; who the leſſe they can ſpeak the louder they do cry, by <hi>a ſilent,</hi> yet potent eloquence to that God, of whoſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes we are aſſured by many Holy, and happy <hi>Tantologies, that they endure for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ Such <hi>Pious, parentall,</hi> and <hi>pathetick</hi> motives here preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to your <hi>Highneſſe,</hi> as from others, ſo from thoſe, whoſe <hi>Oratory</hi> is onely in their <hi>cryes,</hi> and tears; who as tender <hi>Branches,</hi> muſt needs wither, both as to <hi>feeding, and breeding,</hi> if the main root, or ſtem of their Fathers, be either barked round, or <hi>ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed</hi> up, having nothing to do, and nothing to <hi>enjoy;</hi> I ſhall not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118479:11"/>need to adde, that no argument will be more Odiouſly, Bitterly,
<note place="margin">The triumph of Papiſts over the Married, Reformed, and Impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished Clergy.</note> and unanſwerably urged by the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> with their <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> againſt the reformed maried <hi>Clergy of England,</hi> then this; to ſee ſomany of them with their <hi>Wives,</hi> and <hi>Children,</hi> thus expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to moſt <hi>ſordid,</hi> and <hi>ſhamefull neceſſities,</hi> and indeed to perfect beggery; (for many ſuch ſpectacles, my own eyes have ſeen, and my heart deplored) And this in a land of plenty, in a time of peace, and after ſo many high proteſtations, to maintaine the proteſtant, reformed Religion, and incourage the Miniſters of it.</p>
            <p>§ Thus farre (my <hi>Lord</hi>) I have led on my <hi>Petition</hi> for your <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe Clemency,</hi> by the limits of punitive civill <hi>Juſtice;</hi> without making any unhanſome breach, or <hi>incroachment</hi> (I hope) upon its juſt <hi>power,</hi> and <hi>proportions,</hi> in regard to either the juſt offences, or <hi>preſent merits,</hi> of thoſe learned <hi>Scholars,</hi> and <hi>worthy Miniſters,</hi> for whom I have taken this boldneſſe to plead; and in them for their <hi>Wives,</hi> and <hi>Children;</hi> whoſe <hi>numbers,</hi> and <hi>innocency,</hi> are capable to <hi>diſarme the rigors of juſtice;</hi> although thoſe had been actually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by their <hi>Husbands</hi> and <hi>Fathers,</hi> whoſe offences for the moſt part have been and are more in their <hi>perſwaſions,</hi> then their <hi>practiſes;</hi> in other mens <hi>jelouſies,</hi> more then their own <hi>activities;</hi> and ſo their puniſhments hitherto have been rather cautionary, then expiatory.</p>
            <p>§ Nor, (in the ſecond place) will this my humble requeſt,
<note place="margin">Second rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of State urged, for the care of future faſety, and publique peace, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note> any way (I truſt,) ſeeme leſſe <hi>conſiſtent</hi> with your <hi>Highneſſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>igilancy,</hi> and <hi>Frudence,</hi> for the future Peace, and Safety of the Publique; both which in all civil ſocieties, where men have any ſenſe or enjoyment of things beyond <hi>Beaſts,</hi> and <hi>Slaves,</hi> are beſt preſerved as by juſtice, ſo by <hi>equanimity,</hi> and <hi>gentleneſs;</hi> yea, and they are ſooneſt blaſted by two great ſharpneſſe, and ſeveritys, which drawing upon the very <hi>Lees</hi> or <hi>dregs of juſtice,</hi> (ſowred with <hi>jealouſies,</hi> and <hi>revenges</hi>) muſt needs ſavour much, even of injuſtice; For <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> are not more due to offenders, for their malicious <hi>Treſpaſſes</hi> againſt the publique welfare, then ſome mercy and <hi>moderation,</hi> are due to thoſe common miſtakes, <hi>frailties,</hi> and infirmities of life, which oft overttake even worthy men, not ſo much by their <hi>fault,</hi> as by a kind of <hi>fate,</hi> their misfortunes or afflictions being rather tentative of their virtues, then Punitive of their Vices; whoſe even finfull <hi>infirmities,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rigorous ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities enemies to publique tranquillitie.</note> (many times complicated with their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries God <hi>himſelfe</hi> is pleaſed ſo far to conſider, as in the mideſt of <hi>judgement to remember Mercy;</hi> and even to puniſh them more with the relentings of a <hi>Father,</hi> then the exactions of a <hi>Judge; mercy, benignity,</hi> and <hi>compaſſion</hi> being no leſſe beams of <hi>Divine Glory,</hi> and <hi>Majeſty,</hi> than are <hi>Juſtice, Power,</hi> and <hi>Soveraignty:</hi> Theſe are as the <hi>Rubies;</hi> thoſe as the Diamonds of that Crown, which God
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118479:12"/>wears, and indulgeth to <hi>Rulers</hi> on earth, as their Royal Coronets, whoſe extremities and <hi>rigors of juſtice,</hi> muſt never <hi>overlay, or exclude,</hi> their <hi>Chriſtian charity,</hi> and moderation: The want of which St. <hi>Paul</hi> tels us is not the <hi>diminution,</hi> but the <hi>annihilation</hi> of a Chriſtian; yea of a cheif <hi>Apoſtle; For without Charity I am nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ I know the grand Intereſt of publique peace, and ſafety, (which ſeeme the chiefe ground, and ends of that late <hi>Declaration</hi>) are not in reaſon, or policy, to be neglected, by ſuch as ſeek the <hi>reputation</hi> of <hi>prudent ſtatiſts,</hi> and their own preſervation.</p>
            <p>But (my Lord) what wiſe man will ſo farr injure the opinion,
<note place="margin">No publique danger from a few unarm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Miniſters.</note> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally had of your <hi>Highneſſes Potency,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>igilancy in Government,</hi> as to think, that neither your <hi>Highneſſe,</hi> nor the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> can be in a poſture of <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>Safety,</hi> unleſſe ſo many <hi>learned and unarmed men;</hi> many of them <hi>Aged,</hi> and <hi>every way</hi> as <hi>unapt</hi> for warr, almoſt as their <hi>Wives,</hi> and <hi>Children,</hi> unleſſe (I ſay) theſe be quite <hi>undone,</hi> by being <hi>ſilenced,</hi> and <hi>ejected,</hi> from all kind of <hi>Miniſteriall,</hi> and <hi>Scholaſticall imployments,</hi> which are onely ſutable to their breeding, and ability, and competent to maintaine them.</p>
            <p>§ If any man ſhall ſuggeſt, that ſuch <hi>methods of extremityes,</hi> and <hi>deſpaires,</hi> are the proper <hi>Antidotes,</hi> if not to expell the poyſon (as they eſteem it) of <hi>opinions,</hi> already diffuſed in ſome <hi>Miniſters ſpirits,</hi> and veines; yet to ſtop at leaſt the ſpreading, and contagions of them in other men; My anſwer is; That, even in this <hi>point of State policy,</hi> (a depth through which few men can well wade to <hi>Heaven</hi>) I doubt not, but your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> with others, hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; That ſome either leſſe <hi>ſeaſonable,</hi> and <hi>diſcrete rigors,</hi> or more <hi>immoderate ſeverities,</hi> heretofore uſed againſt thoſe <hi>Miniſters,</hi> (whoſe pious, and peaceful <hi>Labours</hi> were uſeful to the <hi>Church of God,</hi> though their judgements in all things were not exactly <hi>conformable,</hi> to the then preſent <hi>conſtitution</hi> of England) even thoſe aſperityes have been thought great <hi>diſadvantages</hi> to the peace, and ſafety of thoſe <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors,</hi> and that <hi>government,</hi> which then prevailed.</p>
            <p>§ <hi>Rigorous exactions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Whether ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions be the way of Safety.</note> and <hi>ſuperfluous ſeverities,</hi> are alwaies weak Reformers of <hi>wilfull men,</hi> much more of <hi>wiſe men;</hi> eſpecially as to their <hi>principles,</hi> and <hi>perſwaſions;</hi> and theſe not onely <hi>inbred,</hi> but inveterate; <hi>ingrafted</hi> by education; <hi>abetted</hi> by conſcience; and confuted onely by the <hi>ſucceſſes,</hi> and the <hi>proſperities</hi> of thoſe, from whom they have ſuffered many effects, of <hi>anger,</hi> and <hi>hoſtility;</hi> but few impreſſions either of <hi>reaſon,</hi> or <hi>Religion,</hi> of <hi>equity, or charity; Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culent methods</hi> of Government, (ſuch as were ſometimes not more exceſſively, then unſeaſonably uſed in the low <hi>Countries,</hi> by the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Alva,</hi> and others,) where people are not more unſetled, then in many things <hi>unſatiſfied,</hi> do but heighten <hi>Animoſities;</hi> by a kind of <hi>antiperiſtaſis;</hi> (as <hi>Salt,</hi> and <hi>Snow,</hi> to water) fixing, and congealing,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118479:12"/>the <hi>malice,</hi> and <hi>deſpite,</hi> as well as the <hi>opinions,</hi> and <hi>perſwaſions,</hi> of men; all which would ſooner diſperſe, and evaporate in milder <hi>wayes</hi> of humanity, and moderation; as the ſpirits of all things do ſooneſt and moſt exhale, in warmer ſeaſons, than in cold.</p>
            <p>§ Nor are ſuch methods, of publique rigors,
<note place="margin">Rigours do not exſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</note> any whit more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable to hinder, or ſuppreſſe, the feared derivation, and traduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of the like principles, and paſſion to others: For your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> well knowes; That all <hi>publique,</hi> and <hi>frequent ſufferings,</hi> in perſons in any repute for <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Learning</hi> (If born with Chriſtian, courage, and conſtancy) do onely move the greater pity, and compaſſion to them in the minds of the <hi>ſpectaters,</hi> and hearers of their calamities; which are by many decryed, by moſt <hi>ſuſpected,</hi> for oppreſſions of power, rather than juſt puniſhments, or <hi>convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> Such ſad and <hi>Tragick ſpectacles,</hi> ſolicite mens <hi>curioſities,</hi> more ſeriouſly to ſearch the grounds of ſo great conſtancy; which <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> tells by his own experience, was a great occaſion, of many <hi>Heathens converſion</hi> to Chriſtianity in primitive times; when nothing invited the world, to regard <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but onely their mutual love, together with their <hi>patience,</hi> and perſeverance in their way; not as <hi>ſullen,</hi> and <hi>obſtinate,</hi> (which <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi> falſly imputes to them) but as deeply <hi>perſwaded</hi> of the truth, and merit of their cauſe or <hi>profeſſion;</hi> of which others grew ſo inquiſitive, when they ſaw them ſo <hi>reſolute.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ From hence, by a native kind of <hi>ſoftneſſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Yea, they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Vulgar, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> mens hearts being as it were melted, they eaſily runne into that <hi>mould,</hi> or <hi>frame,</hi> which firſt they <hi>pity,</hi> then they enquire, afterwards they commend, at laſt they admire; both for the <hi>magnanimity</hi> of the ſufferers, and <hi>ſuppoſed merit of the cauſe;</hi> to which they are ſooner engaged, then they well underſtand it, by a <hi>pricipitancy</hi> of <hi>affections;</hi> which (like <hi>a quick tide,</hi> or <hi>current</hi>) carryes them down the ſtream before their ſailes are well ſpread, or trimmed: For they preſume; That <hi>Cauſe</hi> hath ſomething in it more than <hi>Humane,</hi> which beares up wiſe, and good men, ſo much above humane frailty, <hi>worldly principles,</hi> and ſecular <hi>pleaſures;</hi> At laſt the <hi>inſinuatings</hi> of mans <hi>affections,</hi> and paſſions, (like the motion of <hi>Screwes</hi>) ſecretly, but powerfully ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth their minds, not onely to approve the <hi>cauſe,</hi> but to <hi>emulate</hi> the <hi>heroick</hi> conſtancy of ſuch men; which by degrees, they grow ſo much to love, and applaud on one ſide, that they eaſily <hi>arrive,</hi> to <hi>hating</hi> of the other, and to bitter <hi>reprochings</hi> of thoſe, that are the <hi>implacable</hi> Authors, of ſuch mens ſufferings; in whom they thinke virtue it ſelfe, with Grace, and Truth, yea, Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and God doth ſuffer; Thus opinions, true or falſe, uſually grow, and ſpread more; yea, and take deeper rooting in mens hearts, not only by the reputation of their authors, and abetters,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118479:13"/>but alſo by their being <hi>pruned,</hi> and <hi>cropped,</hi> with <hi>ſharper,</hi> and <hi>ſeverer hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ Your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> cannot be Ignorant,
<note place="margin">The firſt means to allay different Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, &amp; Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in State.</note> that the beſt <hi>medicine</hi> to allay the humors, and inflamations of civil diſſentions in matters of Opinion, is of the ſame temper, and confection, with that, (which <hi>Tacitus</hi>) and other wiſe men, preſcribe againſt <hi>cancerous, rumors,</hi> and <hi>ſcandalous</hi> libels, (which are frequently vented againſt perſons in power, by the eructations of <hi>envious</hi> and <hi>ambitious Spirits,</hi> as thoſe miſts and foggs, which from <hi>valleys,</hi> and loweſt <hi>bottoms,</hi> uſually riſe in the face of Heaven) <hi>Agniti adoleſcunt rumores; ſpreti exoleſcunt;</hi> If they be too much owned, and oppoſed, like torrents or land floods ſtopped in their courſes, they gain <hi>force</hi> and <hi>credit;</hi> If they be neglected, like <hi>Squibs,</hi> they ſpend their <hi>force</hi> and <hi>fury,</hi> without any <hi>danger</hi> or <hi>blemiſh</hi> to <hi>Princes</hi> or <hi>States;</hi> who by a generous <hi>indifferency</hi> diſcover, not onely a juſt <hi>deſpiciency</hi> of ſuch follies; but great confidencies of their own <hi>Integrity;</hi> and ſuch a <hi>magnanimity</hi> as not being eaſily <hi>diſcompoſed,</hi> cannot be wanting to the <hi>maine points</hi> of Safety, and Power.</p>
            <p>§ Nothing,
<note place="margin">The Mutuall cruelties of the <hi>Guelphes,</hi> and <hi>Gibelines.</hi>
               </note> we ſee, kept up thoſe <hi>bloody,</hi> and <hi>bitter warres,</hi> (or <hi>aſſaſinations,</hi> and <hi>maſſacrings</hi> rather) between the <hi>Guelphs</hi> and <hi>Gibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines;</hi> the <hi>Imperiall</hi> and <hi>Papall factions;</hi> for more then one hundred years in <hi>Italy,</hi> and other places, but onely repeated, and <hi>exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant revenges</hi> upon thoſe, who had no other way injured each other, but by their different <hi>perſwaſions;</hi> one preferring the <hi>Popes Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> the other the <hi>Emperours</hi> civill <hi>Power</hi> in the <hi>Empire;</hi> From this principle each party was cruelly <hi>vigilant</hi> to improve the viciſſitudes of Power, &amp; what ever advantages they could get at any time; which they uſed or abuſed rather, not as <hi>lenitives</hi> to compoſe differences, and recover the publique or common <hi>tranquillity;</hi> but as <hi>corraſives</hi> or <hi>ſarcaſmes,</hi> to eat out and wholly <hi>extirpate</hi> the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the <hi>adverſe party;</hi> to the ruing of many worthy men, many noble <hi>Families,</hi> flouriſhing <hi>Cities,</hi> and opulent <hi>Countries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ Doubtleſſe,
<note place="margin">Clemency, &amp; Equanimity, the beſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſtormes as to mens minds.</note> not the bluſtrings of <hi>Boreas,</hi> but the calme Sun-ſhine of generall <hi>tranquillity</hi> ſhining equally, and indifferently, on all honeſt, able, and peaceable men; in any Nation or community, makes them ſooneſt forget their paſt ſufferings; to lay down their <hi>fewdes,</hi> to compoſe their differences, and to conform to that <hi>generall</hi> quiet of which they ſee, they may upon faire termes, have their ſhare; Thus the Flints of civill Factions, are moſt eaſily and ſafely broken on ſofter <hi>cuſhions;</hi> which put between the <hi>anvill</hi> and ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of <hi>Power</hi> and Oppreſſion, are prone to ſtrike fire, and fly in the faces of thoſe who thus ſtrive, not onely to daſh them in peices, but to beate them to powder.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:118479:13"/>
            <p>§ But here (my Lord) I cannot be ſo ſtupidly <hi>indiſcreet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Authors</hi> Apology for touching upon <hi>State Policy.</hi>
               </note> as not to confeſs my <hi>folly,</hi> beſides my fault; and to crave your <hi>Highneſs</hi> pardon, for this ſo great <hi>Impertinency;</hi> by which (as <hi>Phormio a Philoſopher,</hi> who read a <hi>Lecture</hi> of <hi>military Diſcipline,</hi> in the preſence of <hi>Hanniball,</hi> the greateſt, and beſt Commander then in the world, to the no great commendation of his Scholarly Skill, or <hi>diſcretion</hi>) I may ſeem thus weakly, and needleſly to preſent before your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> any methods or rules of Sate <hi>policy,</hi> in reference to publique <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>Safety,</hi> who are knowne both at home and abroad to be ſo great a <hi>Maſter</hi> of all <hi>Arts,</hi> both civill and Military, both in the <hi>practique</hi> and the <hi>Theorie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ This reflection upon my own <hi>fatuity</hi> and <hi>preſumption,</hi>
               <note place="margin">How neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſityes and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperate men.</note> in points of State policy, juſtly forbids me all further needleſſe <hi>importunity,</hi> of ſuggeſting to your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> what you cannot but know, how ſharp an edge <hi>neceſſities</hi> of life nut upon thoſe mens <hi>Spirits</hi> and <hi>activityes,</hi> who otherwiſe are <hi>ſoft</hi> and <hi>blunt</hi> enough; for having no honeſt employment to buſy their thoughts and time, in order to get ſome competent ſupport for themſelves and their families; they cannot avoid to be tempted by <hi>diſcontent, idleneſſe,</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence</hi> to project, and act, thoſe things (though to their own utter ruine) which they hope may either put an end to their <hi>ſufferings;</hi> or at leaſt make thoſe men <hi>ſuffers</hi> with them, (as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did the <hi>Philiſtines</hi>) who ſhew ſo little <hi>compaſſion</hi> to them, and excerciſe ſo needleſs, and undeſerved <hi>ſeverities</hi> upon them; <hi>Paraxiſmes</hi> of anger, diſdain, and revenge oft tranſport even calme and wiſe men, by oppreſſion, (as <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us) beyond thoſe prudent <hi>bounds,</hi> which otherwiſe they had ſet to themſelves; being impatient to ſee themſelves ſo afflicted, as to be deſpiſed; and ſo to be deſpiſed, as to be denied convenient work, and lawful wages in honeſt induſtry: which all humanity, as well as <hi>policy,</hi> allowes; yea, and in ſome caſes commands to thoſe, who are permitted to enjoy their liberty, beyond the <hi>confinement</hi> of a Priſon. We dayly ſee <hi>fires</hi> that are too hot, do quench themſelves, by making even little <hi>pots</hi> over boile.</p>
            <p>§. Certainly, next <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Hell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Sharp Spurre of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty to men of Parts.</note> nothing is more dreadful and intolerable to humane nature, than for men of <hi>skill</hi> to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied <hi>employment,</hi> and men of <hi>underſtanding</hi> to be thereby forced to want <hi>their bread,</hi> which is not to be gotten, but in thoſe Callings that are their proper <hi>ſpheares:</hi> in all other new wayes they are driven to ſeek their food, as <hi>wilde beaſts</hi> in <hi>deſolate places;</hi> which <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etick diſtreſſes</hi> I know have forced very worthy Miniſters to infinite <hi>deſpondencies,</hi> and almoſt <hi>deſpairs;</hi> either having no home for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and their Families; or not enduring their own ſmall and <hi>wretched Cotages;</hi> which are to them like <hi>howling wilderneſſes,</hi> or hell
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118479:14"/>it ſelf; full of <hi>weeping,</hi> and <hi>wailing,</hi> and <hi>gnaſhing</hi> of <hi>Teeth,</hi> for wife, and children's want of <hi>Food convenient</hi> and other <hi>neceſſaries</hi> of Life: The Scripture tells us; <hi>Better are thoſe</hi> that are <hi>ſlain</hi> with the <hi>Sword,</hi> than thoſe that <hi>periſh</hi> by Famine; which is a <hi>lingring</hi> and <hi>multiplied</hi> death; Gods high diſpleaſure threatens the Sons of <hi>Eli</hi> in the ſame <hi>breath,</hi> not only with <hi>early</hi> and immature Deaths; but with thoſe ſharper <hi>neceſſities,</hi> in caſe they live, by which they ſhall be forced to <hi>croutch</hi> for a <hi>morſell</hi> of bread, and ſome <hi>meane imployment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th.
<note place="margin">The Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. for the <hi>Monaſticks</hi> reliefe.</note> (whom Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> ſo blackly and deeply brands for a <hi>perfect Idea</hi> of <hi>Tyranny,</hi>) yet ſhewed (as the <hi>Lord of Cherbery</hi> tells us in the <hi>life of that</hi> King) ſo much <hi>Clemency,</hi> as a <hi>Prince,</hi> and <hi>charity as a Chriſtian,</hi> to thoſe of the <hi>Monaſtick Orders,</hi> when he drave them out of their well <hi>built</hi> and well <hi>honied hives,</hi> as to allow thoſe, who tarried in England, ſome competent <hi>Penſions</hi> during their lives; as knowing, that the way of their <hi>recluſe breeding</hi> in <hi>devout Idleneſſe,</hi> had made them unfit, and ſo unable to get their <hi>living</hi> by any ordinary way of bodily <hi>Labour,</hi> and uſual callings; to which they were indiſpoſed, becauſe unwonted.</p>
            <p>Farre be it then from your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> (who pretend to an higher pitch of <hi>Reformation</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi>) to take away the <hi>remaining frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi>
               <note place="margin">How hard it is to take away the cup of cold water, yet remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to many Miniſters.</note> and <hi>cups of cold water,</hi> from ſo many <hi>Prophets,</hi> and ſome of the <hi>Prophets;</hi> who are not only <hi>men</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> but able Miniſters, as well as Profeſſors of the <hi>Reformed Religion;</hi> Farre be it <hi>from your Highneſſe</hi> (of whoſe bounty I know ſome men of as different perſwaſions to you as <hi>Jewes</hi> are from Chriſtians, have taſted) to break the little <hi>cruſes of oyle,</hi> and barrels of <hi>meale,</hi> which have hitherto ſupplied (as the ſmal <hi>Reſerves</hi> after great <hi>Shipwracks</hi>) the <hi>neceſſityes</hi> of many <hi>excellent</hi> Scholars; who are good <hi>Preachers,</hi> and better lovers of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant Religion:</hi> O let not ſo many godly and grave Miniſters, have cauſe to impute it to your <hi>Highneſſe</hi>'s <hi>Declaration,</hi> that they, their Wives, and Children, muſt during the remainder of their <hi>miſerable dayes,</hi> mingle their <hi>bread</hi> with <hi>aſhes,</hi> and their <hi>drink</hi> with <hi>weeping;</hi> going downe to their <hi>Graves,</hi> oppreſſed with that Sorrow, which is the effect not more of unrelieved than undeſerved Oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>§ I know it will be replyed by ſome;
<note place="margin">Their Charity that put Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments.</note> That <hi>Hungar</hi> is a ſharp <hi>Weapon</hi> as well as a <hi>Sawce;</hi> That <hi>Neceſſity</hi> will quicken mens <hi>Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>Induſtry;</hi> That the <hi>Belly</hi> is a great <hi>Maſter</hi> of art and wit: Let theſe complaining <hi>Miniſters</hi> (ſome ſay) <hi>dig,</hi> and <hi>plough,</hi> and <hi>thraſh</hi> for their <hi>Livings:</hi> or let them turn <hi>Gibeonities,</hi> and <hi>porters,</hi> hewers of <hi>wood,</hi> and <hi>drawers</hi> of <hi>water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus (indeed) the hard <hi>hearts,</hi> and <hi>withered hands</hi> of ſome men, (whoſe very mercies are cruel) are prone to mock at poor <hi>Miniſters
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118479:14"/>calamities:</hi> True; It is of Gods mercy, that any <hi>courſe</hi> of life, or honeſt <hi>labour</hi> will ſuſtain the beſt of us all; who are leſſe than the <hi>leaſt</hi> of Gods <hi>mercies;</hi> and meaner than the <hi>meaneſt</hi> imployment, if it be bleſt with <hi>honeſly,</hi> and <hi>competency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ But I beſeech your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> to conſider;
<note place="margin">No other employments afford them Competency.</note> That beſides the hard <hi>labour,</hi> and ſore <hi>travail,</hi> which muſt needs, in thoſe <hi>manuall,</hi> and <hi>mechanick</hi> wayes, lie upon <hi>ingenuous perſons,</hi> eſpecially in their <hi>age</hi> and <hi>decline,</hi> who have ſpent moſt of their dayes in the ſhadow of their ſtudies, amidſt unactive and <hi>ſedentary retirements,</hi> as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing only with their Pens and Books; Befides (I ſay) this <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comlineſſe</hi> and <hi>unaptneſſe;</hi> There muſt needs follow great <hi>incompeten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> as to the neceſſary <hi>ſupport</hi> of themſelves and their Families, in any ſuch new way; which if it get them bread, will hardly get them any drink, befides cold water.</p>
            <p>§ But befides all theſe conſiderations, the greateſt pity is,
<note place="margin">What pity it is to bury Miniſters ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents in Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</note> to bury the <hi>excellent gifts</hi> of thoſe learned, pious, and Eloquent men under a <hi>Buſhell,</hi> or in the <hi>Earth,</hi> of ſilence, ſordidneſſe, and obſcurity; who are fit to be ſet in <hi>Golden Candleſticks,</hi> in the <hi>Temple of God,</hi> as burning and ſhining <hi>Lights;</hi> among whom Chriſt hath ſometimes delighted to <hi>walk,</hi> and converſe in the excellent <hi>graces,</hi> and uſefull gifts of his <hi>Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ How great a ſinne and ſhame muſt it be,
<note place="margin">Publique Sin and Shame, to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe good Miniſters.</note> as well as <hi>darkneſſe</hi> to this Church and Nation (profeſſing the Chriſtian, and <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion</hi>) not onely to behold, but to cauſe the faces of ſo many <hi>Nazarites</hi> (who have from their youth been <hi>ſeparated,</hi> and <hi>ſanctified</hi> to the ſpeciall <hi>ſervice</hi> of Chriſt, and his Church, who were heretofore <hi>whiter</hi> than <hi>ſnow</hi>) to cauſe them to contract, by ſordid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of living, ſuch <hi>blackneſſe</hi> and <hi>deformity,</hi> as if they had lain among the pots; among the (<hi>lixae &amp; calones)</hi> black guard, which uſually attend <hi>great</hi> mens <hi>Kitchins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ It is great pity, that ſuch goodly <hi>Pillars</hi> of Gods Houſe ſhould be caſt down to the <hi>ground,</hi> and levelled to the duſt, even to the <hi>beaſts,</hi> or <hi>meaneſt</hi> of the <hi>people:</hi> Can it be comely to ſee ſuch <hi>ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> and <hi>laborious oxen</hi> ploughing with <hi>Aſſes,</hi> which God in the Law forbad? It was a ſhame and reproach to King <hi>Jehojakim,</hi> that he buried the <hi>dead body</hi> of the Prophet <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi> in the graves of the <hi>meaneſt</hi> of the people: How much more will it be, to bury Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, even alive among them? That is, ſo to abuſe and cruſh them, as to <hi>enforce</hi> them, either to embrace the <hi>dunghils,</hi> or <hi>converſe</hi> only with clods and clowns.</p>
            <p>§ All which burthens of life muſt needs <hi>preſs</hi> the more ſadly
<note place="margin">No way of competency or comelineſs for Miniſters but their calling.</note> becauſe they are now toward the evening of their dayes, well ſtricken in years; their light <hi>growing dimmer,</hi> and their ſhadowes (both of <hi>fears</hi> and <hi>infirmities</hi>) larger: So that to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118479:15"/>
               <hi>dig</hi> they are not able, and to <hi>begg</hi> they are <hi>aſhamed:</hi> I have known many of them very <hi>grave</hi> and <hi>venerable</hi> men, rather <hi>want,</hi> than <hi>ask;</hi> and contend with <hi>poverty,</hi> rather than <hi>conquer their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity;</hi> Who were wonted to more tender <hi>foreheads,</hi> and a more <hi>bleſſed,</hi> as well as <hi>honorable</hi> way of <hi>giving,</hi> rather than <hi>receiving.</hi> If they be now driven into a deſolate wilderneſſe, they may probably meet with Firy <hi>Serpents</hi> to ſting them by adding contempt to their want. But what Manna or miraculous Food can they exſpect? What rock will follow them to relieve their thirſty and fainting Souls; if they muſt be utterly turned out from any place as <hi>Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> in Chriſts Family, or Diſpenſers of Heavenly Myſteries?</p>
            <p>§ What <hi>commendable frauds,</hi> I boſeech your <hi>Highneſſe,</hi> can there be found for the ſuſtenance of ſo many men, and their <hi>Relations?</hi> Who never have been, nor now are, men of any great <hi>ſecular</hi> dealings, or receipts, and accounts: Such as the unjuſt (but wiſe) <hi>Stexard</hi> uſed for his preſervation; when he ſaw he muſt be caſt out of all bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines, A provident practice which we ſee our Bleſſed Saviour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended; not as to the injuſtice and immorality of it, but as to that worldly prudence and natural policy, or ſagacity; which teacheth and commandeth even <hi>Bruit Creatures,</hi> to be provident for themſelves and theirs; Shewing us, that there is nothing more <hi>Bruitiſh</hi> and <hi>Barbarous,</hi> more <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mnanly</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian,</hi> than to neglect providing for our ſelves, and our <hi>Familyes;</hi> which who ſo doth is worſe than an <hi>Infidel,</hi> and is by the truth declared as an Apoſtate, or denyer of the <hi>Chriſtian Faith;</hi> Sure, if <hi>voluntary</hi> neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and improvidence be ſo much blamed and to be abhorred in reaſon and Religion; There can be nothing commendable, in forcible impoſing thoſe exauctoratings, ſilencings, and reſtraints upon honeſt and Induſtrious men, as muſt compel them to neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>types, when they are more willing to take paines in their callings.</p>
            <p>§ I might further add to the <hi>hunger</hi> and <hi>thirſt</hi> of ſuch mens out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward condition,
<note place="margin">Famine of Souls will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low famished Miniſters.</note> that ſcarcity and famine of the word, which muſt neceſſarily follow in many places: and that <hi>leanneſs</hi> which is like to enter into many poor peoples Souls; to whom ſuch able <hi>men</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly diſpenſed the <hi>bread of eternal life,</hi> as the faithful <hi>Stewards</hi> of Chriſts family; whoſe abſence is not ſo readily to be ſupplied with <hi>Miniſters,</hi> proportionable to their abilityes, induſtry and gravity, as is evident in many ſequeſtred places; where people are either almoſt famiſhed: or at the beſt much infected with the unwholſome <hi>food</hi> of <hi>unſound</hi> doctrine; yea, what if ſuch, as ſucceed theſe outed and able Miniſters, give people <hi>ſtones</hi> inſtead of bread; and <hi>ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions</hi> inſtead of fiſhes! what if they affect to feed mens Souls after the <hi>vaporing</hi> of ſome <hi>novices,</hi> in theſe dayes, with empty <hi>mangers</hi> and <hi>high racks;</hi> giving them the chaffe of <hi>Juvenile</hi> Notions, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118479:15"/>uſeleſſe Speculations, inſtead of thoſe <hi>ſaving</hi> &amp; practical Inſtructions, with which thoſe veterane Teachers, were wont to furniſh and feed their <hi>Auditors</hi> both elder and younger: what account can be given to the <hi>great Biſhop</hi> and Paſtor of <hi>Souls,</hi> if his <hi>Sheep</hi> be ſtarved for want of their Shepherds? If waſt, and weakneſſe, diſeaſes, and death <hi>eternal</hi> fall upon mens precious Souls, for want of ſaving knowledge?</p>
            <p>§ Certainly nothing ſhould be done in civil affairs with more <hi>deliberation</hi> and <hi>circumſpection,</hi> than the ſilencing of <hi>Chriſts Miniſiers;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of changing the Spiritual <hi>Militia</hi> of the Miniſtry.</note> and the divorcing of them from their people, where God hath placed and proſpered them; every one ought to take heed what they do to thoſe that are the ſervants of the moſt High God, and teach the way of Eternal Life. There ſhould be no leſſe <hi>care,</hi> and <hi>caution</hi> in <hi>altering, disbanding</hi> or <hi>caſhiering</hi> this ſpiritual <hi>Militia,</hi> than in that of the <hi>ſecular;</hi> Nor ſhould therein <hi>Reaſon</hi> of <hi>State</hi> onely be conſidered, but <hi>Reaſon</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> with <hi>Chriſts Intereſts,</hi> and the good of <hi>Souls;</hi> for theſe are of eternal <hi>concernment</hi> to poor <hi>mortals,</hi> the other but <hi>momentary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ Since then the temporal welfare of ſo many <hi>worthy Miniſters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The bleſſings accruing to the Publique by able Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</note> by enjoying their <hi>liberty</hi> to <hi>officiate,</hi> is ſo agreeable to the Glory of God, the Honor of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Salvation of poor Sinners, I hope they will not ſeem to your <hi>Highneſſe inconſiſtent</hi> with the publique <hi>Peace</hi> and and ſecurity; yea, ſince there appears no probable means under <hi>God</hi> for the covenient ſupport of ſo many honeſt and uſeful Preachers, beſides other Scholars, but onely your <hi>Highneſſe Clemency</hi> and <hi>Benignity,</hi> in indulging them their honeſt liberty: Since neceſſity drives the <hi>poor</hi> to the <hi>rich,</hi> the <hi>weak</hi> to the <hi>ſtrong,</hi> and the <hi>miſerable</hi> to the <hi>merciful;</hi> yea, even to the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Mercy;</hi> (whom though we cannot move by any <hi>merit</hi> of our own, yet, we may by ſuch humble importunities, as only obtrude upon him our <hi>miſeries;</hi>)</p>
            <p>§ Let it not diſpleaſe your <hi>Highneſſe,</hi> that I have thus far pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed not onely by ſoft and ſuppliant <hi>words,</hi> but by potent and I hope prevalent reaſons, to perſwade you to ſuch <hi>equanimity</hi> and <hi>charity,</hi> as may in real effect obtain ſome ſuch merciful <hi>qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, remiſſions,</hi> or <hi>ſuſpenſions</hi> (as to the execution of your <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> Declaration) That <hi>Pious</hi> and <hi>peaceable Miniſters,</hi> and other Scholars may ſerve God, without diſtraction, and terror, in their wonted <hi>callings</hi> and <hi>imployments;</hi> If any civil caution be neceſſary, beyond your <hi>Highneſſe inreſiſtable</hi> power, and thoſe mens both weakneſſe and danger, no doubt all ſober men will give it,
<note place="margin">Of revoking or remitting the rigors of Publique De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations.</note> as farr as is confiſtent with the <hi>integrity</hi> of their <hi>conſciences;</hi> and further they hope your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> will not require.</p>
            <p>§ Nor ſhall (I hope) that <hi>Scruple</hi> lie in the way of your <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Highneſſe clemency,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:118479:16"/>or my <hi>Brethens</hi> liberty, namely the lothneſſe of <hi>States</hi> and <hi>Potentates</hi> to revoke, remit or qualify any <hi>act</hi> or <hi>edict,</hi> which they have once made publique, leaſt by the ſeeming <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy</hi> of their councels, they ſhould leſſen the <hi>authority</hi> of their <hi>commands,</hi> and the reputations of their wiſdoms.</p>
            <p>§ But herein as your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> hath in the cloſe of your <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> opened ſome little dore of favour and indulgence: So I truſt, no ſevere <hi>reſtrictions</hi> of any Country Committees, or other <hi>Officers,</hi> ſhall be permitted to <hi>ſhut,</hi> or ſtreighten it ſo, as to <hi>exclude</hi> any able <hi>unblameable</hi> and <hi>peaceable</hi> Miniſters, from the ſervice of Chriſt in his Church, by which they may enjoy ſome <hi>compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſubſiſtance,</hi> by ingenous <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>honeſt Induſtry</hi> in their <hi>callings.</hi> Such pious, charitable and generous <hi>Laxations</hi> or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivances as your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> may pleaſe to permit, may amount to the favour by me deſired in their behalfe, without any publique <hi>alteration</hi> or formal <hi>revocation;</hi> of which (yet) no men, never ſo wiſe, and <hi>conſultive,</hi> have any cauſe to be <hi>aſhamed,</hi> when ſuch <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration</hi> is for the better, either as to <hi>verity,</hi> and <hi>equity,</hi> or <hi>charity;</hi> which are not the blemiſhes, but the beauties and bleſſings of <hi>variations, private</hi> or <hi>publique.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ What gracious heart obſerves not with comfort,
<note place="margin">Of Divine retractions, or Gods Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations.</note> that even <hi>God</hi> himſelf the higheſt Pattern of Wiſdom, Juſtice, Power, and Conſtancy, yet, oft and eaſily retracteth as to the event, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of his <hi>Denounced</hi> Wrath; and will rather ſeem <hi>mutable</hi> by his <hi>repentings</hi> (which are mans <hi>impunity,</hi> not Gods <hi>mutability</hi>) than want the <hi>opportunity</hi> of <hi>magnifying</hi> his mercy to penitents; He ſaid he <hi>would deſtroy</hi> them; but he did it not: yea, as willingly ſpared them, as he had juſtly threatned them; being ſolicitous to find a man to ſtand in the <hi>gap,</hi> and turn away his <hi>wrath;</hi> Nay the <hi>Divine goodneſſe</hi> was glad of <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>Interceſſion,</hi> though it ſeemed to be made with an <hi>holy kind of rudeneſſe;</hi> and an <hi>humble diſobedience;</hi> even then when God bad him, Let me alone, that I may deſtroy them.</p>
            <p>§ In like ſort the <hi>Lord</hi> choſe to let his paſſionate and peeviſh <hi>Jonah</hi> ſeem a falſe <hi>prophet,</hi> than himſelf ſhould not appear <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly</hi> true; not ſo much in the <hi>letter of his declared threatnings,</hi> as in the <hi>tacit limitations</hi> and <hi>exceptions,</hi> of his <hi>mercy</hi> and <hi>pardon;</hi> which are ever to be <hi>underſtood</hi> by penitent <hi>ſinners,</hi> though not expreſſed in the menaces <hi>of divine vengeance;</hi> Such gratious <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractations</hi> are not the leaſt part of <hi>a ſinners comfort,</hi> and of Gods <hi>Prayſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ The ſucceſſe which <hi>Moſes</hi> had with God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> his importunity welcome to God though angry.</note> hath emboldned <hi>me firſt</hi> to ſeek to the <hi>throne of his Grace,</hi> by my prayers; Next to make this <hi>petitionary addreſſe</hi> to your <hi>Highneſſe,</hi> not as asking any
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118479:16"/>
               <hi>great thing</hi> for my ſelf; but onely craving thoſe <hi>honeſt freedoms</hi> for other worthy men, which are their greateſt temporal <hi>ambitions;</hi> The granting of which as it cannot any way tend to the diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your <hi>Highneſſe Honor, Profit</hi> or <hi>Safety;</hi> ſo nor will my begging of it, any way I hope tend to your <hi>Diſpleaſure;</hi> But rather your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> will pleaſe to <hi>imitate David;</hi> who incenſed with <hi>Nabals</hi> churliſh ingratitude,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Davids</hi> anger well pleaſed to be diſarmed.</note> and burning with <hi>military flames</hi> of reveng, yet, was neither unwillingly, nor unthankfully taken off from <hi>executing</hi> his intended ſeverityes by the <hi>diſcreet interceſſion</hi> of a wiſe <hi>woman;</hi> for which he bleſſeth <hi>God and her;</hi> Certainly, none are more <hi>exorable,</hi> than <hi>generous ſpirits,</hi> nor any more <hi>generous</hi> than thoſe that have <hi>gracious hearts;</hi> whoſe wiſdome is not <hi>earthly, ſenſual</hi> and <hi>deviliſh;</hi> from their own paſſions, or the <hi>depths of Satan;</hi> but from <hi>above; pure, peaceable</hi> and <hi>eaſy</hi> to be <hi>intreated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ Such <hi>favorable remiſſions</hi> do the fears,
<note place="margin">Publique favours con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer enemies minds.</note> and <hi>dejections</hi> of many <hi>thouſands</hi> of poor <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and their Relations, now crave of your <hi>Highneſſe,</hi> the granting of which cannot but procure your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> many friends; and either ſoften or filence many <hi>enemies;</hi> leaving them without excuſe hereafter; who ſeeing your <hi>power</hi> able to <hi>cruſh</hi> them: ſhall abuſe your <hi>Clemency,</hi> which is willing to preſerve them, in all wayes of honeſt <hi>induſtry,</hi> which becomes them.</p>
            <p>§ But it is now (my Lord) high time for me to be aſhamed;
<note place="margin">Apology for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixity of this Plea.</note> not of my <hi>charity,</hi> (which maketh not aſhamed) but of <hi>tedious,</hi> and exceſſive <hi>prolixity;</hi> conſidering the <hi>Sea</hi> and <hi>moles</hi> of buſineſs, which every moment preſſeth upon your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> (yet, in ſome caſes of great concern, as this is for Gods <hi>Glory,</hi> and the good of ſo many <hi>thouſands</hi> good men, (yea, worthy Miniſters) it would be not onely a great <hi>ſolacifme,</hi> but almoſt a great <hi>ſin</hi> to be ſhort) However this cauſe of ſhame I own; that I have been ſo long in <hi>remonſtrating</hi> or <hi>importuning</hi> that; wherein I not only <hi>underſtand</hi> other perſons of farre more <hi>merit</hi> and <hi>acceptance</hi> have interceded (as the Lord <hi>Primate</hi> of <hi>Armagh</hi>) but I have ſome cauſe to preſume that your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> own purpoſes have prevented me, and all mens mediation; in that you are pleaſed with much candor and gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to admit of any Interceſſors.</p>
            <p>§ Of which benignity I and all the world ſhall then have, not only confidence but <hi>experimental aſſurance,</hi> when your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> ſhall effectually remedy and actually forbid, the further <hi>crying<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,</hi> and <hi>complaining</hi> of ſo many worthy Miniſters and their families in our <hi>Streets.</hi> A <hi>Jeſuitick Jubilee,</hi> which I ſhould not more <hi>pity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Jeſuites Jubilee.</hi>
               </note> than <hi>repine</hi> to ſee thoſe men enjoy, who are very <hi>ſore</hi> and ſubtil <hi>adverſaries</hi> to the <hi>Reformed Religion</hi> and it's ableſt <hi>Miniſters:</hi> Nor do I doubt, that your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> will ever have either more cauſe to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118479:17"/>
               <hi>rejoyce</hi> or leſſe to repent in any thing, that hath or ſhall be either <hi>acted,</hi> or <hi>commanded</hi> by you, than in reviving the ſpirits of ſo many men that are ready to <hi>fayl</hi> within them through diſtreſſe, next dore to deſpair.</p>
            <p>§ Which favorable Indulgence to them will not only turn to an act of <hi>charity</hi> and <hi>humanity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Clemency the beſt ſode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of New Soveranity.</note> but even of true <hi>State</hi> policy too; It being one maxime given by a great <hi>maſter</hi> of it; <hi>Novum impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium inchoantibus utilis eſt clementiae fama;</hi> Though the power of the Sword may here lay the firſt foundation of new government; yet, clemency and moderation, are the chief <hi>cement</hi> and <hi>firmation</hi> of it: The ambition of the <hi>Heathen Grandees,</hi> as <hi>Alexander, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> and <hi>Auguſtus</hi> (firſt Caeſars) alſo of <hi>Trajan, M. Aurelius,</hi> and others, ſought to preſerve to themſelves the <hi>Honor,</hi> and to others the <hi>happineſſe</hi> of their <hi>Clemency,</hi> that they might appear to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, not only <hi>worſhippers</hi> of warlike <hi>Deities,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Bellona;</hi> but alſo of <hi>Jupiter;</hi> who was eſteemed, not only the <hi>King</hi> but the helping <hi>Father</hi> of both <hi>Gods</hi> and <hi>men;</hi> whoſe defective name borrowed its ſupply from the Sacred name <hi>Jehovah;</hi> whoſe glory paſſed by in that <hi>Proclamation,</hi> The Lord <hi>gratious</hi> and <hi>merciful,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>§ <hi>Tertullian's generous</hi> councel is good;
<note place="margin">Chriſtian Charity muſt exceed <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</note> 
               <hi>Plus debet Chriſti diſcipulus, quam mundi philoſophus, gloriae animal, et ſecularis aurae vile manci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium;</hi> Chriſtians act much below their patern, if they do not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the beſt of <hi>Heathens</hi> in <hi>humanity</hi> and <hi>holineſſe</hi> too; as much as their true God doth others <hi>Idols;</hi> Since they have the Word of God for their rule, the Servants of God for their copies; the Son of God for their Original, and the Nature of God for the perfect and eternal <hi>Idaea of all charity, mercy</hi> and <hi>benignity,</hi> who will alſo be at laſt their exceeding great <hi>reward.?</hi> We read that <hi>Joſeph</hi> eaſily ſecured his Brethrens feares of his <hi>reveng,</hi> by telling them he <hi>feared God:</hi> intimating that he was reſolved to follow God in his wayes of <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Gentleneſſe; David a man of Warr</hi> gives it, as one of the <hi>Characters</hi> of a good <hi>man,</hi> he is ever <hi>merciful,</hi> Our bleſſed Saviour enjoynes it to his <hi>Diſciples;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of Mercy and Benignity in Chriſtians.</note> Be ye <hi>merciful</hi> as your <hi>Heavenly Father</hi> is <hi>merciful;</hi> and this not onely to the <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>good;</hi> but alſo to the <hi>bad</hi> and <hi>unjuſt:</hi> yea, God himſelf capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulates with ſuch <hi>wormes</hi> as we are; If we ſhew <hi>mercy,</hi> we ſhall receive <hi>mercy,</hi> according to the meaſure we mete to each other: The <hi>Syrians</hi> gave the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> this <hi>Honor;</hi> that they were merciful Kings; For ſuch as know moſt of the <hi>true God,</hi> will be ready moſt to <hi>imitate him,</hi> in this attribute of mercy, which is above all his <hi>works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ As for my ſelf (my Lord) I have more than my reward, If I have done or endeavoured, as becomes my duty to my God, and Saviour; Next to my conſcience and calling; and laſtly, to that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118479:17"/>charity which I ow my brethren, and fellow labourers; whoſe diſtreſſes I am ſure require, though their <hi>modeſty</hi> did not expect, this ſervice from me, of which they are wholly ignorant; I know many of them, I heare of many more; whoſe worth is not to be meaſured by the falſe weights, and ſcanty meaſure of civil <hi>ſidings</hi> and <hi>factions;</hi> Theſe are many of them reduced to their <hi>cottages,</hi> to their <hi>dry morſels,</hi> to their <hi>water</hi> and <hi>bread</hi> of affliction; which (yet) they greatly feare to looſe; So <hi>much</hi> doth a <hi>little</hi> ſeem to thoſe moderate, and humble minds, who know how to be thankful, yea content, with that which is next door to nothing.</p>
            <p>§ I ſhould ſuſpect my ſelf to be no living member of <hi>Chriſts Body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of Sympathy among Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</note> (whoſe very life conſiſts in <hi>charity</hi> and <hi>compaſſon,</hi>) If I found in my ſelf no <hi>ſympathy,</hi> with the afflictions of ſo many <hi>Joſephs:</hi> yea, I ſhould not onely be aſhamed, but much, and juſtly ſuſpect my own <hi>plenty,</hi> and Gods undeſerved <hi>bounty</hi> to me, leaſt my table ſhould become my <hi>ſnare,</hi> and my very food be digeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into ſin; If I had no ſence, and ſorrow, for others hungry, and afflicted <hi>ſouls;</hi> It were farr better for me to be levelled to the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity of the <hi>meaneſt</hi> of my <hi>Brethren,</hi> (that I might be experience, learn to be compaſſionate) than with an epicurean indifferency, and uncharitable ſtupidity to behold them, wanting <hi>competency,</hi> and indeed <hi>neceſſaries:</hi> which they muſt do; If your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> decree that is gone forth, be rigidly executed; not againſt <hi>Magicians,</hi> and <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> but againſt <hi>grave Divines,</hi> and godly <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the goſpel; to their utter undoing.</p>
            <p>§ It will be favour enough, and a moſt ample returne of my prayers, If by this <hi>pious importunity,</hi> I have any way perſwaded,
<note place="margin">Concluſion deprecating diſpleaſure</note> I have any way perſwaded, (If need be) or confirmed your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> clemency to them. Whoſe pardon I ſhould now (of courſe) formally crave for my ſelf, and thereby add to your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> troubles by ſome ſolemne <hi>apology;</hi> which I would willingly add, if I were conſcious to my ſelf of the leaſt fault in my deſigne; If there be any, it is only ſuch as charity I hope may and will eaſily cover, fince it is charity only that commits it;
<note place="margin">Nor ſin or shame in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</note> Not but that I know ſome moreoſer <hi>polititians</hi> are prone to cenſure even compaſſion for a kind of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, and ſuch <hi>charity</hi> for <hi>malignancy,</hi> (like thoſe <hi>ſcepticks,</hi> who not only diſputed, but denyed the ſnow to be white) but I hope your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> eye will not be leſſe good becauſe theirs are evill.</p>
            <p>§ Onely it is fit to beg your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> pardon for this my into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable treſpaſſing ſo much upon your much oppreſſed time, and little leaſure, by ſo tedious an addreſſe, in which (at the worſt aſpect) I ſhall yet appear as one that pays your <hi>Highneſs</hi> (beſides other taxes) the tribute of double honor; Firſt by owning power
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118479:18"/>in your hand to deſtroy; New, by hoping for pity in your heart to preſerve theſe Miniſters, and other Scholars, in whoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half <hi>I</hi> intercede: who, if any under Heaven, are objects fit for your Clemency, and Compaſſion; both for their eminent <hi>merits,</hi> and their impendent <hi>miſeries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ <hi>I</hi> humbly leave theſe papers in your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> hand; and your heart in Gods; who is <hi>higher</hi> than the <hi>higheſt:</hi> of whoſe mercy we all daily partake, and ſhall while we live on earth ſtand in need; whoſe compaſſions are his good <hi>pleaſures,</hi> but his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>need;
<note place="margin">Peroration.</note> whoſe compaſſions are his good <hi>pleaſures,</hi> but his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, his ſtrange work, as not willingly afflicting the hildren of men: That your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> may in this caſe <hi>imitate</hi> ſo bleſſed a paterne, is the prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>Febr.</hi> 4th 1655.</date>
               <signed>Your <hi>Highneſſe humble ſervant, J. G.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118479:18"/>
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT to the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Good Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou maiſt further underſtand, that at the ſame time, when this Addreſſe was made by the Author in behalfe of thoſe Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> over whoſe heads this Black Cloud then hung, threatning a deluge of deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, God ſtirred up the ſpirit of the then Lord <hi>Primate</hi> of <hi>Armagh,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Uſher,</hi> perſonally to intercede with the then <hi>Oliver Protector,</hi> for his clemency and indulgence toward them; It was one of the laſt endeavours of piety and charity, to which that great and moſt vengerable perſon, applied his moſt potent Intereſſions; fortified not onely by his pious oratory, full of exquiſite reaſon and religion, but with his prayers and teares; For that divine prelate, who was in all things (as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſayes of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) rather admirable than commendable; It being bard to ſay whether be were <hi>doctior</hi> or <hi>melior, ornation</hi> or <hi>humilior,</hi> thought himſelf in nothing more concerned, then in ſhewing thoſe bowels of compaſſion, which became ſuch a Father of the Church, to the worthy ſons and ſervants of it; whoſe afflictions he made his own; nor was he ſatisfied to enjoy ſome degrees of tranquillity and reſpect himſelf, while he ſaw (as <hi>Joſeph</hi>) ſo many of his Brethren, in ſuch great ſtreights and tribulations; He attended <hi>(molliſſima tempora fandi)</hi> the ſofteſt opportunities of mediating for them, five or ſix weeks in <hi>London,</hi> impatient not to ſhew ſuch compaſſion, as became ſo tender an heart, and ſo fervent a Soul as his was; At laſt he was fain to retreate with little ſucceſſe, and leſſe hopes, than he expected and deſerved, to his great grief; uſing this expreſſion, to the <hi>Author</hi> of the foregoing piece, That he ſaw ſome men had onely <hi>inteſtina,</hi> not <hi>viſcera,</hi> guts, but no bowels; Thus did this good man go with ſorrow to his country retirement, and ſo to the grave; preſaging further ſharp impreſſions of Gods ſore diſpleaſure which would ſhortly and ſuddenly light upon this Nation; to the great darkning, as he ſaid,
<pb facs="tcp:118479:19"/>of the reformed Religion, and the depreſſion of faithful Miniſters.</p>
            <p>§ This grand example of Chriſtian commiſeration, (which that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Primate</hi> made more illuſtrious by his eminent worth in all things worthy of a good Man, a good Chriſtian, a good Miniſter, and a good Biſhop) is worthy to be added to the Records of thoſe many other (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) moſt memorable and imitable actions of that Heroe, that Saint, that Angel, of the Britiſh Reformed Churches.</p>
            <p>§ So that the <hi>Author</hi> of the foregoing <hi>Petitionary Remonſtrance</hi> did not alone ſtand in the gap; But was, as in all things elſe many degrees inferiour to that incomparable <hi>Primate,</hi> ſo in this happy to be his ſecond and aſſiſtant.</p>
            <p>§ Which regards are ſufficient to vindicate his endeavours from all ſiniſter reflections; prone to fall from ſuch eyes, as are either more cautious or more envious, and cenſorious than becomes good Chriſtians; eſteeming nothing prudent, which is not ſucceſsful; nor valiant, which is not victorious.</p>
            <p>§ After ages (poſſibly) will be better pleaſed to ſee the afflicted ſtate of the Clergy and Church of England, thus not wholly for ſaken, but aſſerted and compaſſionated; at leaſt by one ſo worthy a perſon; who was as an Army, or cloud of witneſſes; who being ſo well acquainted with the mind of Chriſt, and living in the life of his Spirit; It may be a good omen that in his good time the Father of Mercy, and God of all Conſolation will anſwere his fervent prayer; and return to plead the cauſe, and effectually to intercede in the behalfe of this ſo afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Church, and his Servants the worthy Miniſters of it; who have a long time born the burthen of his ſore diſpleaſure, and the reproach of all unreaſonable men: All which hath not yet drivan them to ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire, but that they pray and hope, in the midſt of Judgement God will Remember his Mercies, which endure for ever: To which Petition all Lovers of Truth and Peace will ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
